<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gods presence mans comfort: or, Gods invisibilitie manifested unto mans capacitie. The heads of which tractate were delivered in a sermon at the Abbey of Westminster, and since enlarged for the benefit of the Church of God. / By the Lords unprofitable servant, Ch. Anthony. Imprimatur: Ja. Cranford.</title>
            <author>Anthony, Charles, 1600-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 188 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75459</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3477</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E328_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8561</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873344</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873344</idno>
            <idno type="VID">159596</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75459)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159596)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 53:E328[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gods presence mans comfort: or, Gods invisibilitie manifested unto mans capacitie. The heads of which tractate were delivered in a sermon at the Abbey of Westminster, and since enlarged for the benefit of the Church of God. / By the Lords unprofitable servant, Ch. Anthony. Imprimatur: Ja. Cranford.</title>
                  <author>Anthony, Charles, 1600-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 91, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.Y. for George Lathum, at the Bishops-head in Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March: 13th 1645"; the second 6 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Song of Solomon II, 9 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:159596:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GODS PRESENCE MANS COMFORT: OR, GODS INVISIBILITIE Manifeſted unto MANS CAPACITIE.</p>
            <p>The heads of which Tractate were delivered in a Sermon at the Abbey of Weſtminſter, and ſince enlarged for the benefit of the Church of God.</p>
            <p>By the Lords unprofitable ſervant, <hi>Ch. Anthony.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>AUG. lib. 6. de TRINITAT.</bibl>
            <q>Qui Trinitatis Myſterium, vel ex parte, vel per ſpeculum, vel ex aenigmate videt, gaudeat; cognoſcens Deum, &amp; gratias agat: Qui vero non videt, tendat per pietatem ad videndum, non per coecitatem ad calumniandum, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam unus eſt Deus, ſed tamen Trinitas.</q>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="lat" subtype="imprimatur">
               <body>
                  <p>Imprimatur:</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Ja. Cranford.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>J. Y.</hi> for <hi>George Lathum,</hi> at the Biſhops-head in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:159596:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:159596:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFULL GILBERT MILLINGTON Eſquire, and all the reſt of the Honourable Committee for the plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Miniſters.</head>
            <head type="sub">As alſo, TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFULL, and his much honoured friend, ROBERT JENNER Eſquire, one of the Members of the Honourable Houſe of COMMONS, Grace, Mercy and Peace from God the Father, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He</hi> glory <hi>of all</hi> Creatures <hi>original<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made by</hi> God <hi>is</hi> Man, <hi>the</hi> glory <hi>of</hi> Man <hi>conſiſteth in the</hi> powers <hi>of the</hi> ſoule; <hi>in them hee excelleth all other</hi> Creatures, <hi>and neereſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembleth his</hi> Creator. <hi>When God would make</hi> Man, (<hi>having before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand made all things for his Being and Dominion) hee ſummoneth (as it were) a</hi> Councell <hi>of the</hi> Trinity,<note place="margin">Gen. 1. 26. <hi>Tilen.</hi>
               </note> Come, let us make man after our likeneſſe: Haec Dei imago in nulla re aſpectabili, praeterquam in
<pb facs="tcp:159596:3"/> homine conſpicitur: Man <hi>onely being endowed with a reaſonable</hi> ſoule, <hi>and adorned with the gifts of</hi> wiſdome, juſtice, equity, ſanctity, <hi>and</hi> verity. <hi>But, alas!</hi> Man <hi>did not ſtand long in this happy condition, but, through the ſubtilty of</hi> Satans <hi>temptations, ſoon fell; (for ſuch is the</hi> malice <hi>of that deſtroyer, that hee labours to hinder the increaſe of heavenly knowledge, and that none may be the</hi> inheritors <hi>of that</hi> kingdome, <hi>of which himſelfe is</hi> diſ-inherited) <hi>and ever ſince, the</hi> powers <hi>of the</hi> ſoule <hi>of</hi> man <hi>are depraved and weakened, ſo that his</hi> Wiſdome <hi>is become</hi> fooliſhneſſe, <hi>his</hi> Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding darkneſſe, <hi>and all is out of order. And as</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind <hi>increaſed in the world, ſo</hi> ſin <hi>increaſed with</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; <hi>and the older the world growes, the more ſinfull it is:</hi> Aetas parentum pejor avis, tulit &amp; nos nequio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. <hi>By this</hi> corruption <hi>of nature, a ſpirituall</hi> dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <hi>hath ſeazed</hi> mans ſoul, <hi>ſo that in heavenly mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters hee is blinde, and the</hi> image <hi>of</hi> God <hi>almoſt blotted out in</hi> him. <hi>Yet hath not</hi> God <hi>ſuffered the whole</hi> light <hi>of</hi> nature <hi>to be quite extinct; for what may be known of</hi> God <hi>is ſeen in the</hi> Creation, <hi>ſufficiently to evince</hi> Atheiſticall <hi>opinions; but more clearly in the</hi> Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, <hi>which, as a</hi> light, ſhine <hi>clearly out of</hi> darkneſſe, <hi>though all cannot perceive it; for all have not faith, (I mean, a true ſaving faith,) and conſequently, all</hi> have not the <hi>true</hi> knowledge of God.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 34.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In this</hi> miſt <hi>of ignorance</hi> Satan <hi>labours to captivate men, and to this effect hee is become</hi> a lying ſpirit <hi>in the</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 22. 22.</note> 
               <hi>mouthes of</hi> Ahabs <hi>falſe</hi> prophets: <hi>and the Apoſtle</hi> Paul <hi>telleth us,</hi> that in the laſt dayes perillous times<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 1, &amp;c.</note> ſhall come, for men ſhall be lovers of their owne ſelves, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Having a form of godlineſſe, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying<note place="margin">Verſe 5.</note> the power thereof: <hi>of whom he forewarneth
<pb facs="tcp:159596:3"/> us,</hi> from ſuch turn away. <hi>The kingly Prophet</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid <hi>alſo telleth us of a</hi> foole that hath ſaid in his<note place="margin">Pſal. 14. 1.</note> heart, (<hi>not with his tongue</hi>) there is no God. <hi>Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they both foretold theſe dayes in which wee live;</hi> irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion <hi>and</hi> impietie <hi>towards</hi> God, <hi>and</hi> unfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <hi>and</hi> uncharitableneſs <hi>towards</hi> men, <hi>being grown to the</hi> heighth; <hi>and</hi> Satan, <hi>that</hi> grand malignant, <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving inſtilled into the minds of ſome</hi> wilfull, heady, <hi>and</hi> unlearned leaders <hi>damnable</hi> hereſies, <hi>whereby the hearts of too too many ignorant people are poyſoned with</hi> ſowre leaven. <hi>Heare Gods judgements againſt ſuch;</hi> Becauſe my people have forgotten mee, they have<note place="margin">Jer. 18. 15, &amp;c.</note> burnt incenſe to vanity, and cauſed them to ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in their wayes from the ancient paths, to walk in paths, and in a way <note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note> not caſt up, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I will ſcatter them as with an Eaſt-winde before the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie: I will ſhew them the back, and not the face in the day of their calamity. <hi>The Apoſtle</hi> Peter <hi>ſpeaks of ſome</hi> unlearned <hi>and</hi> unſtable, who (<hi>in his</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3. 16.</note> 
               <hi>dayes</hi>) wreſted many things in the Epiſtles of <hi>Paul,</hi> as alſo they did other Scriptures, to their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: <hi>So that</hi> hereſies <hi>began to ſpring even in the dayes of the</hi> Apoſtles, <hi>and their immediate ſucceſſors: And although they ſeemed to be</hi> cut down, <hi>and (as it were) buried in</hi> oblivion; <hi>yet now are they</hi> raked up, <hi>and</hi> (Hydra-like) <hi>ſprouted</hi> innumero capite; <hi>wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the many dangerous</hi> pamphlets <hi>of poyſonous opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions lately ſpread abroad: O! happy were it, if they were ſo ſerved as were thoſe</hi> Magick-books at E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus.<note place="margin">Acts 19. 19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>No marvell then if very few ſee God in the true</hi> glaſs <hi>of the</hi> Scriptures, <hi>when the eye of their ſoule hath ſuch</hi> ſcales <hi>to dim them. Some are wilfully</hi> blind, <hi>and will
<pb facs="tcp:159596:4"/> not ſee</hi> God, <hi>like the</hi> Atheiſt: <hi>ſome are</hi> blind, <hi>yet know it not; they ſay they ſee, like the ſelfe-juſtifying</hi> Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees:<note place="margin">Joh. 9. 41.</note> 
               <hi>ſome ſee</hi> God <hi>only in</hi> images, <hi>like the purblind</hi> Papiſt: <hi>ſome ſee him only in the</hi> letter, <hi>not in the</hi> ſenſe, <hi>like the</hi> ceremonious Jew, <hi>or</hi> fantaſtick Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt: <hi>ſome again ſee him onely</hi> obliquely, <hi>in his</hi> free grace <hi>declared in the</hi> Goſpel, <hi>and will not look upon him in his</hi> ſevere juſtice <hi>manifeſted in his</hi> Law, <hi>which (the Apoſtle ſaith) is</hi> holy, juſt, and good, <hi>yea,</hi> ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall,<note place="margin">Rom. 7. 12, 14.</note> 
               <hi>like the</hi> licentious Antinomian: <hi>Whereas all the</hi> properties <hi>and</hi> attributes <hi>of</hi> God <hi>are in himſelfe</hi> eſſentially one and the ſame. Trahit ſua quemque voluptas; <hi>every man will ſerve God after his own fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie, and imagine</hi> God <hi>to be what his dull capacitie conceives him to be. But</hi> Chriſt <hi>hath told us, that</hi> eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry plant that <hi>his</hi> heavenly Father hath not planted,<note place="margin">Matth. 15. 13.</note> ſhall be rooted up. Let then all ſuch beware how they build; for, Other foundation can no man lay,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 10. ad 16.</note> then that is laid, that is, Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c. Upon which place</hi> Calvin <hi>ſaith excellently,</hi> Some preach<note place="margin">Calv. in loc.</note> ſound and edifying doctrine, others mingle idle diſputes of their own brain, more for oſtentation, then for edification of the hearer: now, although theſe are in as good account, and oft-times more, amongſt men, then are the ſoundeſt teachers, yet the day of the Lord ſhall manifeſt their difference. <hi>And when he ſhall viſit them by his Spirit, then ſhall it appear, whether their garments be</hi> fine linnen, clean and white, which is the righteouſneſs of the ſaints,<note place="margin">Rev. 19. 8. Deut. 22. 10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>or</hi> linſey-woolſey, <hi>which is abominable in Gods eyes: then ſhall it appear, whether they break up the Lords vineyard, and</hi> plow his field <hi>with laborious oxen, or not; yea, then it ſhall appear, whether their</hi> ſeed <hi>be</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:159596:4"/> pure wheat, <hi>which may yeeld a plentifull crop, fit to be ſtored up in</hi> Gods granary; <hi>or</hi> tares, <hi>fit only to be</hi> caſt into the fire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nor is it (Right Worſhipfull) that I have adventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (out of any conceit of worth in my ſelfe) to expoſe this enſuing Diſcourſe to the view of the world in this</hi> cenſorious age; <hi>but partly to ſatisfie the</hi> requeſts <hi>of</hi> ſome <hi>who were</hi> auditors <hi>of the chiefe points thereof de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in a</hi> Sermon <hi>in the</hi> Abbey <hi>in</hi> Weſtminſter; <hi>and partly to expreſſe a</hi> gratefull heart <hi>to this</hi> Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Committee, <hi>whom my ſelfe with many others are bound to honour for your vigilancy and care.</hi> Solomon <hi>tels us, that</hi> hee that hath friends muſt ſhew himſelf<note place="margin">Prov. 18. 24.</note> friendly, for there is a friend that ſticketh cloſer then a brother: <hi>And which way can I expreſſe my</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects <hi>and</hi> ſervice (<hi>I owe you) any other wayes, then by imparting unto your</hi> Worſhips <hi>ſome of my weak la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours? Greater gifts you need not; higher prized I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not: I may ſay with the Apoſtles,</hi> Peter <hi>and</hi> John, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>I</hi> humbly <hi>crave par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 3. 6.</note> 
               <hi>for my preſumption, in fleeing to the arms of this</hi> Honourable Court <hi>for patronage of this ſmall Tract, whom I know to be</hi> religiouſly <hi>devoted to</hi> religious exerciſes, <hi>and to accept of this mite thrown into Gods treaſury: God gave liberty (where ability was wanting) to offer under the</hi> Law, <hi>in ſtead of a</hi> lamb, a paire of turtle doves, or two young pigeons. <hi>It may, through Gods bleſsing,</hi> enrich <hi>as well thoſe who ſhall</hi> read <hi>it, as I hope it hath thoſe who have</hi> heard <hi>it. It is not</hi> clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed <hi>with the</hi> rich embroiderings <hi>of</hi> humane elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, <hi>and</hi> wiſdome of words; <hi>I rather chooſe the</hi> Scripture phraſe, <hi>as beſt ſuting to the capacitie and conſcience of my countrey Auditory, amongſt whom I
<pb facs="tcp:159596:5"/> have enlarged it, and of ſuch as may read it: Vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe it (I humbly intreat) your</hi> protection, <hi>and you ſhall ſufficiently reward him, whoſe prayers to</hi> God <hi>for you ſhall be, that you may be filled with a</hi> large mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure <hi>of</hi> grace <hi>in this life, and rewarded with a</hi> full meaſure <hi>of</hi> glory <hi>in the life to come; this he cordially wiſheth, who is devoted to be</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Wor<hi rend="sup">ps</hi>, to be commanded in all Chriſtian ſervice, CH. ANTHONY.</signed> 
               <dateline>Weſt-Hoadligh, in Com. Suſſex.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:159596:5"/>
            <head>GODS PRESENCE MANS COMFORT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>CANT. 2. 9.</bibl>
               <q>Behold, hee ſtandeth behind our wall, hee looketh forth at the window, ſhewing himſelfe at the latteſſe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt worthily is this Book called <hi>Cantica Canticorum;</hi> not becauſe it was penned by the wiſeſt of men that ever was born of a woman by a natural generation, but becauſe in it is ſet down in a moſt patheticall and mutuall colloquie, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable love betwixt Chriſt and his Church un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſimilitude of a Beloved and his Spouſe.</p>
            <p>In the verſe foregoing the Text, as alſo in the former part of this verſe, the Church compares her Beloved (for his care, love, and diligence in haſting to bring comforts unto her) to a Roe or yong Hart; <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith ſhee) <hi>hee cometh leaping upon the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:159596:6"/> and skipping upon the hils;</hi> In the words of the Text ſhee rejoiceth in that ſhee enjoyeth his preſence, thereby <hi>perguſtans ſuavitatem amoris, &amp;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lyra.</note> 
               <hi>future ae beatitudinis,</hi> having got a reliſh of his love, and a taſte of her own future happineſſe, though not ſo fully and perfectly as ſhee would, or as ſhee deſired, nor as hereafter ſhee ſhall: yet in that ſhe hath (as it were) a glimpſe of his perſon whom ſhe longed to enjoy, ſhee exulteth in the words of the Text; <hi>Behold, he ſtandeth behind our wall,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In which words, without wreſting, flow theſe five particulars:</p>
            <p n="1">1. God cannot be ſeen by the eye of mortall man, becauſe of the wall of his fleſh.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Yet God is pleaſed to exhibite himſelfe to man four wayes: 1. By voice. 2. By the book of the creatures. 3. By the book of the Scriptures. 4. By the book of conſcience.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In theſe, it is but hieroglyphically, enigrna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically, obſcurely, darkly.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Yet ſo, that the ſoule of a true Chriſtian by the eye of unblemiſhed faith may be ſure that ſhee ſeeth him in them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That being thus aſſured that ſhee doth ſee him, ſhee may rejoice, and deſire a greater union and communion with him.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not need to inſiſt long to prove whether there be a God or no; I hope there is none ſo A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſticall as to deny it, at leaſt-wiſe with their tongue, although I feare, there are ſome as bad in<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 12.</note> their heart, ſuch as are <hi>without God in the world.</hi> Now of Atheiſts there are three ſorts: Firſt, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts<note place="margin">Pſal. 14. 1. &amp; 53. 1.</note> in thought; <hi>The fool hath ſaid in his heart,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:159596:6"/> there is no God:</hi> that is, as elſe-where the Kingly<note place="margin">Pſal. 10. 11.</note> Prophet explaineth it, <hi>Hee hath ſaid in his heart, God hath forgotten: God will not require it.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">Ver. 13.</note> Atheiſts in words, who ſpeak of God as of no God, <hi>How doth God knew? Is there knowledge in the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 73. 11. Job 21. 14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>moſt High?</hi> Thus the ſeventy ancients of the houſe of Iſrael did horrible things, every man in the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his imagery, and ſaid, <hi>The Lord ſeeth us not.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 8. 12.</note> Thirdly, Atheiſts in converſation; theſe are they that ſo live, as if there were no God, <hi>They profeſſe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1. 16.</note> 
               <hi>that they know God, but in their works deny him. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> did theſe truely know that there is a God, and that hee ſeeth all their abominations, and will at the laſt day call them to a ſtrict account, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely puniſh them, it would make them tremble even in this life: but they are altogether corrupt,<note place="margin">Supra.</note> 
               <hi>abominable, and to every good work reprobate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To omit School-diſtinctions, <hi>Utrum Deum eſſe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aquin. 1. qu. 2. art. 2.</note> 
               <hi>ſit demonſtrabile;</hi> theſe arguments following ſhall ſufficiently prove:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That excellent order of nature, ſeen (both in that Microcoſme or little world [<hi>Man,</hi>] as alſo in that Megacoſme, the greater world, or whole U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſe) in the diſpoſition of parts, and ſucceſſion of motions and actions, which could not be nor ſubſiſt, were there not an Omnipotency to rule and order it; which Omnipotency muſt needs be<note place="margin">Pſal. 8. &amp; 19. &amp; 104. &amp; 135. &amp; 136. &amp; 147. &amp; 148.</note> God, as appeareth by the places quoted in the margent.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That excellencie of humane underſtanding, Man alone being above all other creatures ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall; Reaſon, Knowledge, Wiſdome, &amp;c. being that image of God in man; and in this ſenſe Saint
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:159596:7"/> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> hath it, when he ſaith, <hi>We are his off-ſpring.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 17. 28.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The nature of man acknowledgeth a Deity; for no Nation under heaven is ſo barbarous, but worſhippeth a ſupreme power, either <note n="*" place="margin">2 Kin. 17. 16.</note> creatures, or elſe the workmanſhip of their own hands.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The ſting or worm of Conſcience, even in the moſt reprobate, either in the very act of ſin, or at leaſt after ſin committed, proves a Deity, and that there is a ſupreme Judge, who will call them to an account, which ſting of theirs ſhewes the <hi>law</hi> of a ſupremer power <hi>written in their hearts.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The execution of juſtice in rewarding the godly, and puniſhing the wicked; as in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge drowning all but eight perſons: as in delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Iſraelites, and overthrowing <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his hoſt: as in preſerving <hi>Lot</hi> and his two daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, when Sodom was conſumed: <hi>So that a man</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 58. 11.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall ſay, Verily, there is a reward for the righteous: doubtleſſe, there is a God that judgeth the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you ſee that there is a God; but what this God is, mortall man cannot define, and that for two reaſons:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe he is incomprehenſible.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe his eſſence cannot be known. Yet hath hee been pleaſed to make himſelfe known to us theſe three wayes:</p>
            <p n="1">1. By his Attributes; as his Mercy, Juſtice, Wiſdome, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Goodneſſe to mankind, and Truth: all which are revealed to us, who live within the liſts of the Church; but are not known unto the Heathen, who are without the pales thereof.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By his Perſons, being a Trinitie in Unitie;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:159596:7"/> this wee acknowledge, that <hi>Tota Trinitas unus est Deus:</hi> this the Heathen are ignorant of.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By his works; as of Creation, Preſervation, Rule and Government, which are known to none ſo clearly as they are to ſuch, to whom the ſound of the Goſpel hath come; much leſſe have the Heathen known that bleſſed work of Redemption by Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <list>
               <label>Again, the Attributes of God are either</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Nominall,</item>
                     <item>or</item>
                     <item>Reall.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Nominall; as <note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 15. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Jehovah,</hi> which ſignifies an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Being of himſelf: this Name he took unto himſelfe, thereby to point at, and ſhadow out un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us his Eſſence, which is incomprehenſible; by this Name <note n="†" place="margin">Exod. 6. 3.</note> hee was not knowne unto <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> but by the name <hi>Shaddai,</hi> which ſignifies Almighty; that was a name of Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency, this a name of Majeſty: Or <hi>Jah,</hi> that is, Lord, becauſe hee is the <hi>Alpha</hi> of all things: Or <hi>Elohim,</hi> which ſhewes to us the diſtinction that is to be made of the Perſons of the Trinitie, <note n="*" place="margin">Mal. 1. 6.</note> the Father, <note n="†" place="margin">Luk. 1. 35.</note> the Son, <note n="*" place="margin">Acts 2. 4.</note> the Holy Ghoſt: Or, as in the New Teſtament, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as being the firſt Eſſence of all things: hence is hee called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſole Lord Paramount, becauſe hee hath his Being in and of himſelfe, and dependeth on none other: Or, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe he ſeeth or compaſſeth all things. Other nominall Attributes there are, as <hi>El, Abba,</hi> &amp;c. but I omit them, and haſten to his reall Attributes, ſuch are they that are onely proper unto God, and ſhew his divine Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
            <list>
               <label>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:159596:8"/>Such are either</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Abſolute,</item>
                     <item>or</item>
                     <item>Relative.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Abſolute, as his Perfection, being ſolely of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and giving life and being to all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the world: or his Infiniteneſſe, or Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, being <hi>principii &amp; finis expers,</hi> having neither beginning of dayes, nor length of time: or his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſibilitie, not having any bodily ſhape, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to be diſcerned by humane ſenſe: or his Immutabilitie <note n="a" place="margin">Mal. 3. 6.</note> in his Eſſence, <hi>I am the Lord, I change not;</hi> in his <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 33. 11.</note> Will, <hi>The Counſell of the Lord ſtandeth for ever;</hi> or in his <note n="c" place="margin">Jer. 23. 24.</note> Place, <hi>I the Lord fill heaven and earth:</hi> or his Omnipotency, for <hi>quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid vult facit,</hi> hee doth whatſoever pleaſeth him. To theſe I might adde his relative Attributes, as Knowledge, Wiſdome, Goodneſſe, Juſtice, Truth, Liberality, Bounty, Mercy, &amp;c. Relative I call them, becauſe in God they are eſſentiall, in man accidentall; in man finite, but in God infinite, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible, inviſible.</p>
            <p>Now all theſe Attributes are given unto God <hi>pro nostro captu, vel ratione cognitionis noſtrae,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of us men, and for our benefit; by which that light which is in it ſelf inacceſſible, may after a manner be ſhadowed out to the dim eye of our dull apprehenſion, which is not able to behold ſo reſplendent a Majeſtie: for the glory of God doth far more excell the glory of the Sunne, then the light of the Sunne doth the light of a candle. Well may wee therefore admire, and ſay, O the heighth,<note place="margin">Rom. 11. 33.</note> the breadth, the length, and the depth of the Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niteneſſe and Inviſibilitie of Almighty God! yea,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:159596:8"/> and pray alſo with the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>That wee may</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 3. 18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>be able to comprehend with all ſaints, what is the breadth, and length, and depth, and heighth;</hi> that ſo wee may be filled with the fulneſſe of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, whom to know <hi>is life eternall.</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 17. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now there are foure degrees or windowes, by and thorow which the preſence of this God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly ſhineth to the eye of our ſouls.</p>
            <p>The firſt whereof is univerſall, whereby in his<note place="margin">Jer. 23. 24. Pſal 139 7. &amp;c.</note> Eſſence hee is fully every-where, incluſively no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; <hi>totus eſt in toto mundo, &amp; totus in qualibet mundi parte.</hi> And as hee is thus univerſally preſent in his Eſſence, ſo is hee alſo in all his eſſentiall Properties, as his <note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 147. 5.</note> Wiſdome, <note n="e" place="margin">Deut. 9. 29.</note> Power, <note n="f" place="margin">Exod. 2. 5, 6.</note> Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is ſpeciall, whereby hee is ſaid to be in heaven <note n="g" place="margin">Eccleſ. 5. 2. Pſal. 19. 1, 6.</note> becauſe there his glory, power, wiſdome and goodneſſe are ſeen in a moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent manner; from whence alſo he ſhowers down<note place="margin">Acts 14 17.</note> in a moſt plentifull ſort his bleſſings upon us for our temporall benefit.</p>
            <p>The third is moſt ſpeciall, as hee dwels by his gracious and ſanctifying Spirit in the hearts of his elect and choſen; ſo much S. <hi>Paul</hi> affirmes, <hi>Know</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 16.</note> 
               <hi>ye not that ye are the Temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth is moſt ſpeciall and ſingular, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when hee is preſent by his Spirit in Chriſt: ſo S. <hi>Paul, In him (viz.</hi> Chriſt) <hi>dwelleth all the fulneſſe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2. 9.</note> 
               <hi>of the Godhead bodily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet in none of theſe can the brightneſſe of the Deity be ſeen by the eyes of humane fleſh: and the reaſon is twofold; Either,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:159596:9"/>1. <hi>Ex parte objecti apparentis,</hi> in regard of the excellency of Gods glorious Majeſtie appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Or,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Ex parte ſubjecti videntis,</hi> in regard of mans infirmitie in beholding.</p>
            <p>For the firſt cauſe: Such is the Majeſtie and brightneſſe of Almighty God, that the moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Angels, the Seraphims and Cherubims, are<note place="margin">Iſa. 6. 2.</note> forced to cover their faces at his preſence: And if ſuch created natures, yea rather, ſuch ſpirituall ſubſtances, cannot ſee that <hi>incorporeall uncreated</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hom. 14. in Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han. Dialog. tit.</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutabilis.</note> 
               <hi>Vertue</hi> (as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> calls it,) or (as <hi>Theodoret</hi>) that <hi>incomprehenſible divine Subſtance,</hi> much leſſe can man. If that ſaying of Chriſt be objected, <hi>Matth. 18. Their Angels alwaies behold the face of my Father:</hi> I anſwer, The Angels ſee God, but it is according to their capacitie and ſtrength; not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the divine Subſtance, for that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible: And S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, that <hi>it is one</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. 12. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Paulin.</note> 
               <hi>thing to ſee, and another thing to comprehend the whole by ſeeing, when as nothing of the whole is concealed, but all is ſeen round about in every part thereof.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, If that Citie which is above be ſo glorious, as Saint <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks, the <hi>wall is of Jaſper, the Citie</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 21. 18 &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>it ſelfe of pure gold like unto cleare glaſſe,</hi> that <hi>it need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the Sunne or Moon to ſhine in it,</hi> &amp;c. how glorious then is the Lord God, whoſe <hi>glory is the light thereof?</hi> As then a man may be upon the ſea, and yet not exactly know the full breadth and depth of the ſea: even ſo the Angels themſelves, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they are in heaven, and ſee God really in his glory; yet cannot they fully comprehend either the<note place="margin">Ludovic. Grata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſis lib. 1. duc. peccat.</note> depth of his Majeſtie, or the altitude of his Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:159596:9"/>
            <p>The divine Eſſence is of that perfect beauty, and of that excellent glory, that man is not able to comprehend the fulneſſe of Gods Majeſtie; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>No man</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>John) hath</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John 4. 12. 1 Tim. 6. 16.</note> 
               <hi>ſeen God at any time. Hee onely</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul) hath immortalitie, and dwels in light which no man can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach unto, whom no man hath ſeen, or can ſee.</hi> So holy <hi>Job, Loe, he goeth by me, and I ſee him not: hee</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 9 11. &amp; 23. 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>paſſeth on alſo, but I perceive it not. Behold, I goe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, but hee is not there; and backward, but I cannot perceive him: On the left hand where hee doth work, but I cannot behold him; hee hideth himſelfe on the right, that I cannot ſee him. Verily,</hi> (ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet<note place="margin">Iſa. 45. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Iſaiah) thou art a God that hidest thy ſelfe, O God of Iſrael the Saviour. Deus ubi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> praeſens eſt, attamen</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. in Hom. in Ezek.</note> 
               <hi>vix inveniri poteſt; ſtantem ſequimur, at apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere non valemus:</hi> Hee is above us, and below us, before us, and behinde us, on either ſide of us, yea, within us, yet we can neither ſee him, nor feel him. <hi>Per molem corporis nuſquam eſt: per incircumſcriptam</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem.</note> 
               <hi>ſubſtantiam nuſquam deeſt.</hi> Hee is above us by his power ruling us, hee is below us by his ſuſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion relieving us, hee is without us by his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe environing us, and he is within us by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit piercing the very ſecrets of our hearts.</p>
            <p>For the Eſſence of God conſiſteth not of mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, as doth an humane body; nor of affections, as doth the ſoul of man: and although members, as hands, eyes, ears, feet, &amp;c. yea, and paſſions of the minde, as anger, jealouſie, patience, &amp;c. are divers times aſcribed to God in his word; yet are theſe termes aſcribed to him none otherwiſe then by an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, according
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:159596:10"/> to the weakneſſe of our capacitie; for his perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on admits not of the leaſt weakneſſe or pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Simonides</hi> the Poet, being demanded by <hi>Hiero</hi> the Tyrant, what God was, craved a day to delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate; and not being then able to define the true Nature and Eſſence of God, hee craved two daies more; that time being paſt, and himſelfe yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſolved, hee craved four dayes, ſtill doubling his number: and being demanded the reaſon hereof, hee anſwered, that the more he ſtudied and dived into that abyſſe, the leſſe able was hee to define what God was; ſo incomprehenſible is Gods Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
            <p>In a word, whatſoever can be ſaid of God, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not fully expreſſe his infinite Immenſity. <hi>Cujus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. in Moral.</note> 
               <hi>ergo gloriae non ſufficit obstupeſcens conſcientia, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo ſufficiet loquens lingua?</hi> If then the aſtoniſhed conſcience of man cannot ſufficiently conceive the Majeſtie of God, how then can his tongue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it?</p>
            <p>O! then admire the length, breadth, heighth, and depth of this Deitie, whoſe length is Eternitie, whoſe breadth is Charity, whoſe heighth is Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, and whoſe depth is Wiſdome: <hi>Qui amat ut</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern. in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derat. Dei.</note> 
               <hi>Charitas, novit ut Veritas, ſedet ut Aequitas, domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur ut Majoſtas,</hi> &amp;c. Who loves as cordially as Charity, knoweth all things judicially as Verity, judgeth uprightly as Equity, rules royally as Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, governs potently as Principalitie, protects impregnably as Safety, works mightily as Power, helps readily as Pietie, and is manifeſted as the Sun in his ſplendour gloriouſly. His power is inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable,<note place="margin">Hug. Card. lib. 1. de clav. ani.</note>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:159596:10"/> his goodneſſe incomprehenſible, his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ineffable, and his definition is alwayes to be praiſed by his holy ones. Thus much for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of Gods glorious Majeſtie appearing, which cannot be ſeen by our bodily eye.</p>
            <p>The ſecond cauſe of mans not ſeeing God is, his infirmity in beholding; and this is twofold: Either,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Through the guilt of ſin: Or,</item>
               <item>2. Through the frailty of his fleſh.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Through the guilt of ſin. When God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared<note place="margin">Exod. 3. 6.</note> to <hi>Moſes, Moſes</hi> hid his face, becauſe hee knew himſelfe to be a ſinfull man. The guilt of ſin makes a man conſcious to himſelfe, and afraid to look even an earthly Judge in the face, much more to behold ſo glorious a Majeſtie as is the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence: thus <hi>Adam</hi> went and hid himſelfe<note place="margin">Gen. 3. 8.</note> when he had tranſgreſſed, by eating the forbidden fruit: And if (when the voice of God walked in<note place="margin">Note.</note> the cool of the day) hee hid himſelfe, oh! how would hee have trembled if God had come in the heat of the day? When Chriſt was transfigured upon the Mount, and his face did ſhine like the<note place="margin">Mark 9. 6.</note> Sun, and his raiment was white as the light; <hi>Peter</hi> and the other Apoſtles were afraid, and knew not what to ſay: So alſo, when <hi>Peter</hi> ſaw the Majeſtie of his Maſter in that great draught of fiſhes, he falls down at Jeſus his feet, and ſaith, <hi>Depart from mee, O</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 5. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Lord, for I am a ſinfull man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh then! ſith horrour of conſcience in regard of ſin makes men afraid of the face of God, that men would remember, that <hi>his eyes are upon the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 34. 21, 22.</note> 
               <hi>wayes of man, and hee ſeeth all his goings. There is no
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:159596:11"/> darkneſſe nor ſhadow of death, where the workers of i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquity may hide themſelves.</hi> As alſo, that nothing terrifies the conſcience ſo much as doth the guilt of ſin, which is the mother of fear. Conſcience is that book in which all our ſins are regiſtred; <hi>Et</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caſſiod. lib. 4. Epiſt. 8.</note> 
               <hi>quid acquiri putatur, ubi mala conſcientia praedicatur? aut, in qua parte poſsit homo proficere, ſi innocentiam probatus fuerit amiſiſſe?</hi> What can be gained where conſcience preacheth terrour? or, what can a man plead for himſelf, if guilt of ſin tortures and terrifies? A ſinfull guilty conſcience cannot endure to behold ſo infinite a Preſence, but ſoon ſhall be ſwallowed up with ſo glorious a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond cauſe is the frailty of mans fleſh: for ſuch is the weakneſſe and tenderneſſe of the eye of man, that hee is not able to behold the Sun in <hi>Rota,</hi> when in a clear day he is as in a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot adorned in his glorious ſplendour, then which no creature is brighter; for the more a man gazeth on it, the blinder is his ſight. The Iſraelites were<note place="margin">Exod. 34. 30.</note> not able to behold <hi>Moſes</hi> his face when hee came from talking with God on mount Sinai, <hi>they were afraid</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>to come nigh him,</hi> untill hee had put a vaile over it: And if man cannot endure to behold that glory wherewith God hath inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted his creatures, how much leſſe able is hee to behold <hi>ipſam vim divinae Eſſentiae,</hi> that infinite glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of that infinite God, who gave ſuch glory to his creatures? for the workman is alwayes of more excellent aſpect then the work it ſelfe, as the pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is more honourable then the clay, and the builder of the houſe of more eſteem then the houſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:159596:11"/> builded. As then glaſſe cannot endure the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent-working heat of the fire, without either break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or melting; no more is man able to behold Almighty God, who <hi>is a conſuming fire,</hi> without<note place="margin">Heb. 12. 29.</note> periſhing.</p>
            <p>Againe, God cannot be ſeen by the bodily eye of man, for then hee ſhould be of ſome humane ſhape, and wee ſhould conceive groſly of him, <hi>juxta paſsibilitatem humanam,</hi> according to vaine fancy: <hi>Behold,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) the heaven, and the</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chro. 6. 18.</note> 
               <hi>heaven of heavens cannot containe him:</hi> Heaven is his throne, and the earth is his foot-ſtool; and as he is of infinite Immenſity, and cannot be circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed within any bounds or limits; ſo is his Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence inviſible and incomprehenſible, and cannot be ſeen by the frail eye of man.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Moſes</hi> deſired to ſee Gods face or glory, that is, the fulneſſe of Gods glorious Majeſtie, the Lord told him that it would be hurtfull to him, <hi>Thou canſt not ſee my face and live,</hi> ſaith God: <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tali</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exo. 33. 18, &amp;c. <hi>Bibl. Interlin.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>carne Deum videre non potuit.</hi> Such was the glorious ſplendour of Almighty God, and ſuch the weakneſſe of his dazled eyes, that although his deſire was great, yet his infirmitie was greater; hee could not ſee the face of God in full Majeſty: God indeed vouchſafed to ſhew him his back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts, which ſome interpret his wondrous works; others, Gods attributes and properties, by which God mightily made himſelfe known to <hi>Moſes;</hi> but his glory, or his glorious Eſſence, by his mortall eye hee could not ſee. As wee are not able to know the eſſence of any ſtar; ſo are wee not able to reach to the knowledge of the Eſſence of God.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:159596:12"/> While man is clothed with fleſh, hee is ſubject to weakneſſe, yea, hee is weakneſſe it ſelfe. Even the eye, which is the light of the body, is not capable of things other then what are ſublunary; nay, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them it cannot diſcern perfectly: but when this earthly clod is laid in the duſt, and this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption hath put on incorruption, and this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality hath put on immortality, then ſhall hee ſee God (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) face to face; that is, hee ſhall ſee God in greater perfection, although even then hee ſhall not be able to comprehend him in his Immenſitie. In this life the Church knoweth him either by hearing his voice, or by ſeeing him ſtanding behinde a wall, or elſe look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing through grates or lattiſes; that is, in the book of the Creatures, or the book of the Scriptures, or the book of Conſcience: And this brings mee to the ſecond generall of the Text, in which is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently manifeſted the exceeding love of ſo infinite a God, who vouchſafeth to impart himſelfe unto man by familiaritie; not by exhibiting his Eſſence, but by ſending forth his voice.</p>
            <p>In the foregoing verſe of the Text, the Church<note place="margin">By Voice.</note> rejoyceth in that ſhee heares the voice of her Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved. It is by voice that God is pleaſed wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to make himſelf known unto his own. Thus by voice did hee make himſelf known to the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs before the Law, to the Prophets under the Law: and thus did Chriſt manifeſt himſelfe at his Baptiſme, and at his Transfiguration.</p>
            <p>This voice of God ſounds ſometimes terribly; as at the giving of the Law, when <hi>there were thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 19. 16.</note> 
               <hi>and lightnings, and a thick cloud upon the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:159596:12"/> Mount, and the voice of a trumpet exceeding loud, ſo that the people trembled:</hi> Obſerve the place; Trumpets ſounded mightily in the aire, fearfull thunders brake forth from out the skie with fierce light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, with horrible miſts, with thick clouds, and terrible ſmokes ariſing from the mountain; and, in the midſt of all this, a dreadfull terrour of the voice of Gods more dreadfull Majeſtie, <hi>I am the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. Whence obſerve, that ſithence the Law of God was delivered with ſuch trembling, that wee alſo tremble to violate this Law, and the rather, becauſe the exaction of this Law ſhall be with greater terrour at the laſt and generall day of Gods great aſſiſes, then the publication of it was with aſtoniſhment. Daily experience teacheth us, that the violation of the lawes of earthly Princes are executed upon delinquents with greater ſeverity then they were proclaimed: Even ſo Almighty God, by his voice in giving the Law, ſpeaks, threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens, and thunders, in each denouncing open war againſt all ſuch as ſhall contemptuouſly offer vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence unto his Law: hee will be avenged <hi>on his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 46. 10.</note> 
               <hi>adverſaries,</hi> and comfort himſelfe in their deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Thus alſo when Chriſt deſired his Father <note n="h" place="margin">John 12. 28, 29.</note> to glorifie his Name, a mighty <hi>voice came from heaven, ſaying, I have both glorified it, and will glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it againe;</hi> inſomuch, that <hi>the people ſaid, it thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred.</hi> And ſometimes this voice comes mildely, as when the Lord appeared to the Prophet <hi>Elijah;</hi> for firſt there came a violent <hi>winde,</hi> which <hi>rent the</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 19. 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>mountaines, and brake the rocks in pieces;</hi> yet <hi>the Lord was not in that winde:</hi> then <hi>an earth-quake,</hi> yet <hi>the Lord was not in that earth-quake:</hi> then <hi>a fire,</hi> yet <hi>the</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:159596:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:159596:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:159596:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:159596:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:159596:15"/> 
               <hi>Lord was not in that fire:</hi> laſt of all came <hi>a ſtill ſoft voice,</hi> and in it God was. To ſtubborn and incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous<note place="margin">Note. Pſal. 68. 33.</note> people God <hi>ſends forth his voice</hi> with fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: but to obedient and beleeving people, in love and mercy.</p>
            <p>Now if God manifeſteth himſelfe by voice, then not by Imaginary conceits, like the ungodly perſon, who (as <hi>David</hi> obſerves) runs the road of<note place="margin">Pſal. 50. 18, 21.</note> all villany, joining with the theef, partaking with the adulterer, and opening his mouth with the ſlanderer, and thinks God to be ſuch a one as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Nor yet by Imagery draughts, as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts would, who picture him like an old man ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in a chaire, groſly abuſing his Divine Eſſence. Beloved, none can conceive ſo holily, ſo reverent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſo divinely of God in every reſpect as hee ought; therefore hath God given an eſpeciall charge to the Jewes (and in them to us) concerning his worſhip, to <hi>take heed,</hi> becauſe they <hi>ſaw no ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 4. 12, 15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>they onely heard a voice out of the fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And a voice there was, to teach us, that as God at firſt taught the Jewes by a voice; ſo likewiſe in theſe dayes, and to the worlds end, God will uſe and ſanctifie a voice to men for their ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Naturally indeed man inclineth to that which affecteth the eye and other outward ſenſes; and this is a notable bait in Popery to adore goodly images, and as the Athenians the ſhrines of <hi>Diana,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 19. 34.</note> thereby to bewitch the common people, and theſe they call the Lay-mans books: but in the mean time, the chiefe inſtrument, the voice, is either altogether taken away or elſe uttered in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known tongue, which cannot edifie. Thus doe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:159596:15"/> they feed the peoples greedy-eyes, whiles in the mean time they ſterve their hungry ſoules. God hath (and bleſſed be his Name that hee hath) thought good to manifeſt himſelfe unto us by voice; and to this end hath hee given to us the organ of the eare, <hi>to heare what the Spirit ſaith unto</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 2.</note> 
               <hi>the Churches:</hi> hee then that hath an eare is bound to heare; for this wee may conclude on, that they who will not be inſtructed by hearing, are paſt hope of ſaving, for <hi>faith cometh by hearing:</hi> and,<note place="margin">Rom. 10. 17. Heb. 11. 6.</note> 
               <hi>without faith it is impoſsible to pleaſe God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If then wee deſire truely to know and ſee God, let us diligently prepare our hearts, as well as the eares of our bodies, to that meanes which God hath appointed to bring us to the knowledge of him; that ſo, whether the Lord ſhall ſpeak ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther immediately by his owne voice unto our ſoules, or mediately by his Miniſters, wee may be ready to anſwer with <hi>Samuel, Speak Lord, for thy</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 3. 10.</note> 
               <hi>ſervant heareth.</hi> For (Beloved) God cannot but be offended, if we ſhall doe like thoſe Jewes of whom he complaineth, that <hi>ſay one to another, Come (I pray)</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eze. 33. 30. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>and hear what is the word that cometh forth from the Lord; and they come unto thee as the people cometh, and they ſit before thee as my people, and they heare thy words, but they will not doe them. And loe, thou art unto them as a very lovely ſong of one that hath a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant voice, and can play well on an inſtrument, for they hear thy words, but they do them not.</hi> O, Beloved! while the Angel of the Covenant cauſeth his voice<note place="margin">Mal. 3. 1.</note> to be heard in our Land, let us in the feare of God be attentive and attendant; and above all things, deteſt wee Popery, which would quite blindfold
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:159596:16"/> the eyes of our ſoules for ever ſeeing Chriſt ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing behinde our wall, and deafen our eares from hearing him in his ordinances, and leave us to read him only in dumb images.</p>
            <p>Againe, ſeriouſly conſider, and judge in your owne conſciences, what a ſottiſh ſtupidity it is for any to goe about to expreſſe a Being infinite by a thing finite. Hear Gods own words by the mouth of that Evangelicall Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, To whom will</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 40. 18.</note> 
               <hi>yee liken mee (ſaith the Lord)? or, what likeneſſe will yee compare mee unto?</hi> In which very words is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſhown, that none can make an Image a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to reſemble Almighty God; <hi>All</hi> things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared<note place="margin">ver. 17.</note> to <hi>him are as nothing,</hi> nay, <hi>leſſe then nothing,</hi> even <hi>vanity:</hi> ſo then, Man cannot conceive any thing whereby to expreſſe this incomprehenſible Majeſtie. Beſides, it is a moſt blaſphemous vilify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this divine and ſpirituall Eſſence, to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny figure or ſimilitude of it at all; for it makes us to conceive carnally of God, when as carnall ſhapes can no whit expreſſe him: <note n="a" place="margin">Joh. 4. 23.</note> 
               <hi>God is a Spirit,</hi> and ſpirituall <note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 14.</note> things muſt be <hi>diſcerned ſpiritually.</hi> The exacteſt Image of pureſt metall is but the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of mortall man, and without life, and therefore can no way ſet forth him who is life it ſelf, and giveth life and being unto all things.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But Chriſt is as well Man as God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as Man, he may be figured by an Image.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> Hee that maketh the Image of Chriſt as hee is Man, leaveth out the chiefeſt part of him, namely, his Divinity, which maketh him to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Lords Annointed: But his Divinity and his Humanity are inſeparable: Hee then that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:159596:16"/> preſumes to make ſuch an Image, ſeparateth that which God hath joined, and makes himſelfe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed, by <hi>turning,</hi> not the <hi>image,</hi> but the nature and ſubſtance <hi>of the incorruptible God into the image</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 23. &amp;c.</note> of <hi>corruptible man;</hi> thus <hi>changing the truth of God into a lie, worſhipping and ſerving the creature more then the Creatour, who is bleſſed for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Divers other reaſons might be brought to prove the folly of Idolatry. Let this one obſervation ſuffice to ſtop all Papiſts mouthes: If a voice can be pourtrayed, then may the Eſſence of God be pictured.</p>
            <p>Wherefore let us deteſt Poperie, the beautie of which doctrine doth onely conſiſt in the externall repreſentation of this eternall Deity: and let us know, that whom the minde of man cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, him the tongue of man cannot expreſſe, much leſſe can the work of mans hand figure out or pourtray. And ſith God hath been graciouſly pleaſed to manifeſt himſelfe unto us by voice, then which nothing is ſhriller; let us be carefull and attentive to hear him, when hee ſpeaketh unto us, either by his owne immediate voice, or by the voice of his Miniſters; or whether hee be pleaſed to manifeſt himſelfe unto us by the book of the Creatures, or the book of the Scriptures, or the book of Conſcience; which now I come to handle in their order, being the ſecond part of the ſecond Generall.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God manifeſtly exhibiteth himſelf<note place="margin">By the book of the Creatures.</note> unto us by the book of the Creatures, which are various and innumerable.</p>
            <p>The Kingly Prophet <hi>David,</hi> admiring the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:159596:17"/> of the glory of God ſeen in his creatures, (<hi>when I conſider</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>the works of thy hands</hi>)<note place="margin">Pſal. 8. 3.</note> falls preſently into a deep conſideration, both of the work of God in man, as alſo of the love of God towards man; <hi>What is man?</hi> Becauſe then man is the moſt excellent viſible creature of all, and the image of God is more lively deciphered in him then in any, or in all other creatures what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, let us ſee how many wayes man readeth unto us a lecture of this Deity.</p>
            <p>God may be ſeen in man four wayes:</p>
            <list>
               <label>If we conſider,</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Who made him.</item>
                     <item>2. Whereof he was made.</item>
                     <item>3. In what forme.</item>
                     <item>4. To what end.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. If we enquire who made man, <hi>Moſes</hi> (the pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of God) will tell us, that God made him. <hi>Come, let us make man:</hi> the whole Trinity had<note place="margin">Gen. 1. 26.</note> hand in the creation of man. The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> hath the like phraſe; <hi>O Lord, thou art our Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 64. 8.</note> 
               <hi>wee are the clay; thou art the potter, we are all the work of thine hands.</hi> And, (ſaith that holy Pſalmiſt) <hi>Know</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 100. 3.</note> 
               <hi>yee that the Lord God is hee that hath made us, not wee our ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. If wee enquire, Of what man was made; See wee, His ſubſtance was <hi>the duſt of the ground,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 7.</note> and even that at firſt was of nothing; ſo that man originally is nothing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If we enquire, Of what form man was made, <hi>Moſes</hi> alſo tels us, that <hi>in the image of God God crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 1. 26, 27.</note> 
               <hi>him;</hi> which image (as I have already ſhowne) is Wiſdome, Knowledge, &amp;c. <hi>Imaginis hujus ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectum
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:159596:17"/> animam eſſe rationalem dicimus, ſanctitatis, &amp;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tilen. de imag. Dei, in hom. theſ. 8.</note> 
               <hi>veritatis, &amp; juſtitiae dotibus exornatam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. If wee enquire the end why man was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; It was for Gods glory: Now God is then glorified by man, when man cometh to the true knowledge of God, and loveth him with all his heart, with all his ſoule, with all his ſtrength, and maketh him the true and onely object of his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. <hi>Homo principaliter conditus eſt ad celebrationem</hi>
               <note place="margin">u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſin. Cat.</note> 
               <hi>Dei, hoc eſt, ad profeſsionem &amp; invocationem nominis Divini, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt of theſe is ſeen the goodwill and pleaſure of God, in that hee would make ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a creature as man. In the ſecond is ſeen the power of God, in that hee could make him. In the third is ſeen the love of God, in that he would make him after his owne Image. In the fourth is ſeen the wiſdome of God, in that hee would make him a rationall creature: jointly together, they all ſhew that neer conjunction that ought to be of man with God, and how earneſtly man ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a fuller enjoyment of his preſence and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, who is unto man all in all.</p>
            <p>So then you ſee that man is to be conſidered in a double reſpect. Firſt, as hee is a creature: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, as endued with a rationall ſoule; of both which God is the principall authour. Our parents indeed were the inſtruments of our fleſhly being under God; for without God they could not doe that, for <hi>the fruit of the womb</hi> is the bleſſing of the<note place="margin">Pſal. 127. 3.</note> Lord: And if the parents of the fleſh were the onely and ſole inſtruments of generation without God, then might they exactly know how many
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:159596:18"/> muſcles, nerves, veins, bones of all ſorts, humours, and joints were in the body, yea, where and how located; but this they know not, even the skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulleſt Anatomiſt may fail herein: hence ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>I am fearfully and wonderfully made,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">Pſal. 139. 14, 15, 16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, if the Parents of our fleſh had the ſole and onely power in our making, then, when our body is ſick, they might recover us; or, if any mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber were rotted away, or cut off by violence, they might reſtore it: but this neither can they doe. Sith then God is the principall cauſe of the bodies being, which is earthly, wee may well conclude, that hee onely created the ſoul, which is ſpirituall, and that our earthly parents had no ſhare in the creating of that at all: <hi>Quod ex carne natum eſt, caro</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh 3 6.</note> 
               <hi>eſt; That which is born of the fleſh, is fleſh:</hi> But the ſoul is immortall, created onely by God, he onely it was who <hi>breathed in</hi> man <hi>the breath of life.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Adde to this, the union of the ſoul with the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which makes the body to be compleat, could not be effected by any other, ſave onely that pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull Worker, whoſe word is a law; no skill but Divine could unite them twaine together. As then wee are creatures, as wee are rationall creatures, wee ſolely are the work of his hands, that is, of his Wiſdome, and of his Will. Hence are thoſe ſayings in Scripture: <hi>Thy hands have made mee, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 33. Job 10. 11.</note> 
               <hi>faſhioned me round about. Thou haſt clothed mee with skinne and fleſh, and fenced mee with bones and ſinewes:</hi> And, ſaith the mother of the ſeven ſons, <hi>I know</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Mac. 7. 22, 23.</note> 
               <hi>not how yee came into my womb, for I neither gave you breath, nor life, nor was it I that formed the members of every one of you. But doubtleſſe the Creatour of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:159596:18"/> world, who formed man, and found out the beginning of all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, conſider we whereof man was made, <hi>viz.</hi> of the earth, which is ſlimie and filthie, and which wee tread under our feet: By how much therefore man is made of viler ſubſtance; by ſo much it ſtands him upon to be lowly and humble, knowing that as hee is of the duſt, ſo to duſt hee muſt returne, and that duſt at laſt ſhall be reduced to its former nothing; for, ſaith <hi>Peter, The heavens</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3. 7.</note> 
               <hi>and earth that are now, are by the word kept in ſtore, reſerved unto fire againſt the day of judgement.</hi> 'Tis true, that body which wee ſhall have at the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reſurrection, although it ſhall be the ſelf ſame fleſh with which wee are now cloathed, ſhall yet be incorruptible: it ſhall not be, as now it is, earthy, animated onely by a ſoul ſeparable; but it ſhall be ſpirituall, all danger of ſeparation being done away by Chriſts Spirit quickning it, if wee be inheritors of the kingdome of heaven: ſo much the words of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> import, <hi>Fleſh and bloud</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 50.</note> 
               <hi>cannot inherit the kingdome of God;</hi> where, by fleſh and bloud, the Apoſtle meaneth bodies earthy and fraile. Nor may wee think with <hi>Origen,</hi> that<note place="margin">Mayer. in loc.</note> our bodies ſhall not then conſiſt of fleſh and bones, as now they doe, and that the fleſh ſhall be abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, becauſe they are then called ſpirituall: But, as here, our bodies are called animall, becauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimated by the ſoule, they both being kept toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by means of ſuſtenance; Even ſo then, our bodies are called ſpirituall, becauſe perfectly gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the ſpirit, and vivified unto a life, that, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without all ſuſtenance, ſhall never have end:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:159596:19"/> And, that this is the Apoſtles meaning, is evident, when hee ſaith, <hi>Corruption doth not inherit incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Conſider wee the forme in which man was created: <hi>God created man after his own image;</hi> it is not ſaid, <hi>after his own ſimilitude: Imaginis enim vox eſt</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the word ſignifies diverſly: ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it may be taken for the very Eſſence of God, and ſo onely Chriſt is ſaid to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 1. 15.</note> 
               <hi>of God:</hi> Or, more emphatically, as the ſame Apoſtle, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the expreſſe image</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1. 3.</note> 
               <hi>of his perſon:</hi> Or elſe the word may be taken as ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifying Wiſdome, Juſtice, &amp;c. which I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved formerly. Again, Man was created or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>after Gods image,</hi> not of <hi>Gods ſubstance:</hi> As then the ſubſtance of which man was made was more vile, ſo the image in which hee was made was more glorious: Nor doe I mean the outward ſhape of man conſiſting of members and linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of body, though that alſo be exceeding glorious above the ſhape of all viſible creatures whatſoever, (<hi>Os homini ſublime dedit,</hi> &amp;c.) for the outward ſhape of man is accidentall, not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall; but I mean the ſubſtantiall part of man, which makes him to be the glory of all creatures, conſiſting in reaſon, underſtanding, and will, in which hee neereſt doth reſemble his Creatour. <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mago Dei homo est, non ratione corporis, ſed ſpiritûs; Deus enim Spiritus eſt, non corpus.</hi> And as a man is thus the image of God, hee hath dominion over all other creatures: For it is worth obſervation, that man hath his preheminence over other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, not in regard of ſuch things as are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:159596:19"/> to him with them, as ſwiftneſſe, ſtrength, bulk of body, or the like; for wee ſee that crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are far ſwifter, much ſtronger, more corpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent then man: but in regard of reaſon, will, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, &amp;c. His glory conſiſteth not in things common to him with brute beaſts, but in thoſe things of which they are not capable. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude therefore this third Obſervation, As the beauty of the body conſiſteth in the members well proportions, and in comelineſſe of complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſo doth the beauty of the ſoule conſiſt in the light of underſtanding, reaſon, and will: For when the ſoule of man ſhineth with wiſdome, and his will with uprightneſſe, then is God ſaid to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light<note place="margin">Pſal. 49. 20.</note> in man; but when <hi>man,</hi> whom God hath thus <hi>created to honour, hath no underſtanding, hee is</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared <hi>to the beaſts that periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Conſider wee the end why man was created, and that is twofold: Firſt, intrinſecall, or inward, and ſo a thing is then ſaid to be made, when the end for which it was made is fully fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and compleatly perfected: thus a Palace is then ſaid to be finiſhed, when all things requiſite to the full adorning thereof are ſo compleat, that nothing more is wanting: Thus alſo a tree is then ſaid to be a good and perfect tree, when it ſpreads forth its branches, ſhoots forth its leaves, and brings forth good fruit. And in this ſenſe is man ſaid to be created, when hee attaineth unto that end for which hee was created; namely, when hee hath attained to eternall happineſſe; which ſhall be, when hee ſhall enjoy the fulneſſe of Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and be transformed into his image. The<note place="margin">1 John 3. 2.</note>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:159596:20"/> ſecond end why man was created is extrinſecall, or outward; namely, to manifeſt unto the world the glory of that God who<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> created him; and this by offering to God <note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 50. 23. Joſh 7. 19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>prayer and praiſes,</hi> by <note n="f" place="margin">Rev. 7. 15.</note> 
               <hi>ſerving him day and night,</hi> by confeſſing his mercies, and <note n="g" place="margin">Num. 20. 12.</note> 
               <hi>ſanctifying him in the eyes of the people;</hi> which is done by beleeving on him, and, if God ſhall ſee good, to ſuffer the loſſe of all, even life it ſelfe, for Chriſts cauſe and the Goſpels, O happy hee who<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 16.</note> is <hi>not aſhamed</hi> to <hi>glorifie God on this behalfe.</hi> As then the outward end why a Palace was built, was for the honour of him that builded it, as <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> could vaunt; <hi>Is not this great Babel that I have</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 4. 30.</note> 
               <hi>built, for the houſe of the kingdome, by the might of my power, and for the honour of my Majestie?</hi> Or, as the cauſe why trees are planted is for the pleaſure and benefit of him that planted them: even ſo the end why man was created, was to ſet forth the glory of the Creatour; for God created him for himſelf. All other things are made for man, and man alone is made for God: and this gives mee two other Obſervations worthy your heedfulleſt attention.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That all things created by God, either in the heavens, earth, or ſeas, are not ordained for themſelves, but for the uſe and ſervice of man:</hi> Thus the heavens emptie themſelves upon the earth, to make it fruitfull, and the earth again returneth her fertili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and all is for the behoof and benefit of man, man onely is reſerved for the glory of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That all other things ſpend themſelves to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and enrich man, yet cannot man enrich God:</hi> God ſtands not in need of mans performances, <hi>Nullâ re
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:159596:20"/> indiget Deus,</hi> ſith <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 50. 10, 11, 12.</note> all things are at his command. The totall reward, gain, and profit of mans ſervice to God redoundeth unto man. So wonderfully excellent is God in all his works, ſo ſuperabundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gracious is hee to his chiefeſt work, man: and yet in a more peculiar manner is hee like a tender Father to them that fear him, in that hee hath laid up for them <hi>a crown of life,</hi> and himſelfe will be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<note place="margin">Rev. 2. 10.</note> them <hi>a diademe of beauty.</hi> And what is this<note place="margin">Iſa. 28. 5. Matth 25. 21.</note> Crown, but an entring <hi>into the joy of</hi> our <hi>Lord,</hi> a fruition of eternall reſt with glory, which is a good beyond all apprehenſion? ſo ſaith S. <hi>Paul,</hi> repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Iſa. 64. 4. 1 Cor. 2. 9.</note> it out of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, Eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, neither hath it entred into the heart of man to conceive the things which God hath prepared for them that love him.</hi> Sith then God hath thus provided for man, man is obliged to glorifie God. This may ſuffice to have been ſpoken concerning God manifeſted in man, or how the image of God is ſeen in man.</p>
            <p>Our next diſcourſe ſhall be the Heavens, in which God hath placed thoſe glorious lights of the world, the Sun, the Moon, and the Starres, ſo extolled by that Kingly Prophet, <hi>When I conſider</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 8. 3.</note> 
               <hi>the heavens,</hi> &amp;c. In which let us ſee how God is pleaſed to manifeſt himſelf unto us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The heavens declare the glory of God, and the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 19. 1.</note> 
               <hi>firmament ſheweth his handy-work, being all glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly adorned, and curiouſly beſpangled with ſtarres.</hi> Nor doth the prophet onely mean the heavens, but, by a Synecdoche, the whole fabrick of the world; for there is not the leaſt angle of the world, but even in it, after ſome certain manner,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:159596:21"/> the eternall power and God-head is manifeſted; but becauſe the glory of God is more exactly and apparently engraven in the heavens, then in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther irrationall creature, therefore hee the rather names them, whoſe glorious ſplendour is ſeen un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all throughout the world; yea, he layeth down the manner how the wiſdome and power of God is diſcerned in them in the enſuing verſe, <hi>One day</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 19. 2.</note> 
               <hi>telleth another, and one night certifieth another:</hi> that is, they evidently declare, that they were not made by chance or fortune, but by that moſt wiſe and omnipotent Architector, even by that moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Creator, whoſe glory they doe manifeſt. So that, if man had no other book to read God in, but onely the book of the Creatures, the Heavens themſelves would ſufficiently declare the Majeſtie, the Power, and the Goodneſſe of Almighty God: For, conſider how God hath placed in the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the heavens thoſe glorious creatures; <hi>the Sun to rule the day, the Moon and the Starres to govern the night:</hi> nor doe they rule by their own power, but by that power which they receive from God their Creator.</p>
            <p>In the Sun the holy Ghoſt ſetteth down three remarkable things, and worthy our beſt obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it is a moſt glorious creature, adorned<note place="margin">Pſal. 19. 5.</note> like <hi>a Bride-groom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That it <hi>runs</hi> alwaies, and that moſt ſwiftly<note place="margin">Verſ. 5, 6.</note> and ſtrongly <hi>like a Gyant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 That from the Suns reflection all other things receive their vegetation; for <hi>nothing is hid from the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 6.</note> 
               <hi>heat thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:159596:21"/>1. The Sun is a moſt glorious creature, and therefore compared to a <hi>Bride-groom going forth of his chamber:</hi> and wee know that then are men al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes beſt bedecked, when the day of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſals are come, that they may ſeem moſt love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the eyes of their Bride. But if wee were able perfectly to behold the body of the Sunne for its immenſity and quality, wee ſhould not need this compariſon of a Bride-groom to illuſtrate its inexpreſſible beauty. All the beauty of the eye conſiſteth in light; if the light be gone, and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe cover the face of the earth, the eye can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcern nothing. And becauſe nothing is ſo ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and lovely as the light, therefore would God be pleaſed to be called light; <hi>God is light, and in</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John 1. 5.</note> 
               <hi>hind there is no darkneſſe.</hi> And in this light of the Sun wee may ſee him who is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 1. 17.</note> 
               <hi>of lights,</hi> even light it ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Sunne is alwayes in a very ſwift and wonderfull motion; hee <hi>rejoyceth as a Giant to run his courſe:</hi> Now in a Giant, according to his greatneſſe and ſtrength, ſo is his ſwiftneſſe; but the Sunne is farre ſwifter then any Giant, when in the ſpace of four and twenty hours hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſeth his Orbe: and who can but in this alſo ſee the ſtupendious wiſdome, and admirable power of Almighty God?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Nothing can hide it ſelfe from the light thereof; the Moon and the Starres, the Air, the Earth, and the Seas all borrow their light from this light, and all receive their maturity from its heat; yea, even the Mines under the earth have their production from it: And as the earthy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:159596:22"/> receive their nouriſhment from the Sun, even ſo the ſoules of men receive their enlightning from God, who is the <hi>Father of lights. Sol pater eſt luminum corporalium, Deus verò luminum ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualium:</hi> The Sun indeed is the father of lights corporall, but Almighty God is the Father of lights ſpirituall.</p>
            <p>And as the power and glory of God is ſeen in the Sun, which is the glory of the day; ſo alſo are his power and providence ſeen in the viciſſitude and changes of the Moon, which is the governeſſe of the night. And this creature affoords theſe two doctrinall Obſervations:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That as the Moon is neerer to the Sun, the brighter is her body towards the heavens, and the darker towards the earth: Or, when ſhee is in conjunction with the Sun, ſhee is bright upwards towards the Sunne, and dark downwards towards the earth; ſo on the contrary, when ſhee is in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the Sun, her body is dark towards the heavens, and bright towards the earth; all her light then reflects downwards, none upwards. So in like manner, (for I ſhall conſider man like the Moon, and God like the Sunne;) when man (like the prodigall) is gone from the Sun of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe into a farre countrey, then that light of his underſtanding (wherewith God had endowed him) being abuſed, reflects onely earthward, his thoughts are onely <hi>minding earthly things:</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though<note place="margin">Philip. 3. 19.</note> to the eye of the world this man is judged and eſteemed to be the onely wiſe and happy man, yet perhaps in the eyes of God hee is poor, blinde, and naked. On the other ſide, when a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:159596:22"/> wicked man turnes from his wickedneſſe, and proves a true convert, a faithfull beleever, <hi>an Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elite indeed, in whom there is no guile,</hi> hee is then ſubjected to God by humilitie, and knit, or in a manner in conjunction with God by charity in an holy union; ſo that <hi>Quae ſurſum ſunt quaerit, Hee minds the things that are above, where Chriſt ſitteth</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3. 1.</note> 
               <hi>on the right hand of God:</hi> then alſo his underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is heavenly, and <hi>from above, it is pure, peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 3. 17.</note> 
               <hi>gentle, eaſie to be intreated,</hi> &amp;c. It is not ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did, that is, <hi>earthly, ſenſuall, divelliſh.</hi> And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though<note place="margin">Verſ. 15.</note> to the eye of the world hee may ſeem ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, forlorn, deſpicable, and accounted no better then the <note n="d" place="margin">Jer. 8. 2. Zeph. 1. 17.</note> 
               <hi>dung upon the earth,</hi> and even <note n="e" place="margin">Job 18. 17. Iſa. 26. 14.</note> 
               <hi>as a dead man out of minde;</hi> yet is he dead only to the world, but <note n="f" place="margin">Col. 3. 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>his life is hid with Chriſt in God,</hi> and <hi>therefore when Chriſt, who is our life, ſhall appear, hee alſo ſhall appear with him in glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. By this changing of the Moon, God would give us to underſtand how frail man is, how ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to fall from his God by ſin, and therefore how carefull hee ought to be in ſeeking a perfect union and communion with God, and to turn to him betimes, <hi>quia neſcit an aliàs reverti dabitur, nam qui promiſit poenitentibus veniam, &amp; reverten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus gratiam, non promiſit longiorem vitam, nec poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentiae donum ſponte peccantibus:</hi> becauſe hee who hath promiſed pardon to the penitent, hath not promiſed longer life to repent; hee who hath vouchſafed to conferre grace to them that truely turne unto him, hath not promiſed the gift of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance to wilfull and obſtinate ſinners, ſuch as abuſe the riches of his mercy. <hi>Let us therefore</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 4. 16.</note>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:159596:23"/> (while wee have grace offered) <hi>come boldly unto the throne of grace, that wee may obtain mercy, and finde grace to help in the time of need.</hi> And let us know, that the neerer wee draw unto God, the brighter will the beams of his countenance ſhine upon our ſouls: not but that the Lord is pleaſed ſometimes (as it were) to cloud himſelfe from us; and this hee doth in his wiſdome, and on purpoſe, that wee may both more earneſtly long after him, and more highly prize his preſence when wee enjoy it. <hi>In</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> 
               <hi>omnibus ſanctis hoc facit Deus, ut ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tribulationes, neque jucunditates continuas ſinat habere.</hi> God deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thus with all his holy ones, that neither the burthen of afflictions may oppreſſe them, to make them deſpair; nor the flaſh of proſperity puffe them up, to make them preſume. Hear Almighty God by his Evangelicall Prophet: <hi>For a ſmall moment</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 54. 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>have I forſaken thee, but with great mercies will I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thee. In a little wrath I hid my face from thee for a moment, but with everlaſting kindneſſe will I have mercy on thee, ſaith the Lord thy Redeemer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor are the Starres without ſome expreſſion of the Deity; <hi>Species coeli gloria ſtellarum, mundum autem illuminat Deus:</hi> The beauty of heaven is the glory of the Starres, but God is the glory of the world: for whatſoever beauty is either in the Sun, the Moon, or the Starres, is borrowed from God, <hi>who is the Father of lights;</hi> and they, in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſet forth unto man that excellencie and power of God: for in their order they manifeſt the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, and in their obedience to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand they ſhew the power of his Will, they ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a delight to obey their Creatour.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:159596:23"/>
            <p>Again, The Starres ſet forth the workmanſhip of their Creator, both in their ſwiftneſſe of their motions in their proper courſes (for in their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſpheres they are alwayes moving,) as alſo in their ſweet harmony and muſick obſerved by <hi>Job;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 38. 31. &amp;c.</note> which harmony is not to be heard by the eare of the body, but of the ſoul and underſtanding.</p>
            <p>Thus from the beauty and vertue of the Sunne, Moon, and Starres, as wee may gather not a little of the knowledge of God, ſo wee may conceive more of that eternall bleſſedneſſe which all they ſhall enjoy who ſhall be citizens of the new Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, in that they ſhall exceed even the <note n="*" place="margin">Matt. 13. 43.</note> Sun in his luſtre and glory.</p>
            <p>I could long inſiſt in this book of the creatures, having a large ſubject to diſcourſe on; but I will ſhun tediouſneſſe, and briefely diſcourſe of them generally.</p>
            <p>Man at his firſt creation was a perfect creature, yet mutable; at firſt hee was endowed with a ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of knowledge, yet ſubject to fall, and ſo to come ſhort of that firſt perfection.</p>
            <p>Not long after mans creation, through the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till temptations of Satan, <hi>Eve</hi> was beguiled, and<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> ſhee perſwading her husband to eat, both ſinned, and fell ſhort of that their former happineſſe. Since which time, much of that knowledge in which hee was created is impaired; for whereas before hee was able readily to diſcern the vertue and nature of all things, yea, and to give names to every creature agreeable to that their nature and vertue; hee now falls ſhort, and hardly can with much labour and ſtudie finde out the vertue of any
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:159596:24"/> vegetable. Whereas before hee was Lord over all creatures, and might both command and teach; hee may now from them learn leſſons worthy ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation: All his ſenſes are now ſo depraved and weakned, even in things naturall, that it is no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell if hee faile in things ſpirituall. <hi>The oxe knoweth</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 1. 3.</note> 
               <hi>his owner, and the aſſe his maſters crib; but Iſrael doth not know,</hi> &amp;c. So that now the brute creature muſt read a lecture to man, whereby he may come to the knowledge of his Creator. And if man di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently obſerve the varietie and nature of the creatures, together with the wonderfull fabrick of the world, he ſhall finde them as a ſhop or ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, full of various wonders, and wonderfull variety, of ſecret myſteries, and myſticall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets; or as a Schoole, wherein hee may reade large lectures of deep Divinity, the world being as a book in folio, every page whereof is written full of his excellent works, and thoſe in capitall letters, inſomuch <hi>that hee that runneth may reade.</hi> Excellently doth the ſon of <hi>Syrach</hi> ſet for the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom<note place="margin">Ecclus 43.</note> and power of God in the variety of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and yet ſaith he, <hi>Who can magnifie him as he is?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 31.</note> Yet nevertheleſſe, by theſe his works in the world, and governance thereof, man may in part diſcern the Juſtice, the Knowledge, the Wiſdom, the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and the Providence of God: for God hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted certain ſparks of his beauty unto his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, thereby to draw us to the conſideration of the love of him who is <hi>Pulchritudo ipſa,<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Beauty it ſelfe, and whereof all other is but as a ſhadow: Even as a man, finding a ſmall current of water, may thereby be moved to ſeek out the head of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:159596:24"/> ſpring; or, as happening on ſome ſmall veine of gold, may be thereby animated to ſearch out the mine it ſelfe. But wee, alas! like ſilly children, delight our ſelves onely with the faire cover of the book, not minding what is contained within: Whereas, in all fair creatures which daily wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, wee ſhould rather conſider thus within our ſelves, that if God could make one clod of earth ſo amiable, by imparting unto it ſome ſmall ſparkle of his excellency; how infinitely faire muſt hee then be in himſelfe, yea, how worthy all-love and admiration, who is ſole perfection? yea, and how happy wee then ſhall be, when wee ſhall enjoy his beautifull preſence, from whence all creatures doe borrow theirs? But (as I ſaid) commonly wee onely reſt in the externall appearance of viſible objects, and carry not our contemplations from the creature to the Creator.</p>
            <p>In the old Law God commanded, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever<note place="margin">Lev. 11. 41, 42.</note> did goe upon its breaſt, ſhould be abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation unto man: Oh! how abominable then is reaſonable man, who hath his ſoule as it were glewed to the creatures, even to this white and yellow clay? yea, and how vaine are they that pride themſelves in their apparell, borrowing from all creatures to make themſelves ſeem lovely? from one they borrow wooll, from another his skin, from another his furre, from others even their excrements; as ſilk from the worm, and perfume from the cat: and not content herewith, but they borrow pearls from fiſhes, ſilver and gold from the earth, and precious ſtones from the ſtands; and theſe they hang about their bodies, to draw the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:159596:25"/> eyes of others to ſtare on them, as if this beauty were their own: for when the ſtone glitters upon their finger, they in their own conceit glitter alſo; and when the ſilk ſhines on their backs, Lord! how proud are they in their own fancies! never conſidering that God who infuſed that beauty even into thoſe creatures from whom they bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed it. So that, although the creatures of the world doe wonderfully ſet forth this great God; yet every man ſeeth not God in them, onely the true Chriſtian, the Spouſe of Chriſt, can diſcern him thorow theſe grates, can perceive him from behinde this wall, and that onely by the cleer eye of unblemiſhed faith. Not that the manifeſtation of the Deity is debarred any man, for Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>The inviſible things of God from the creation of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 20.</note> 
               <hi>the world are cleerly ſeen, being underſtood by the things that are made, even his eternall power and Godhead:</hi> So that it is plain, that God is made manifeſt unto all, even by the works of the creation, although all do not obſerve it.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But God is inſenſible, that is, inviſible, and therefore not cognoſcible:</hi> quod enim non cadit in ſenſum, non ſubit intellectum; <hi>that which comes not within the compaſſe of our ſenſe, comes not within the verge of our underſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> God conſidered in himſelf, that is, in his Eſſence, is indeed inviſible, according to S. <hi>John,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>No man hath ſeen God at any</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John 4. 12.</note> 
               <hi>time:</hi> yet is his inviſibility manifeſted and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in the things created; for, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>that which may be known of God is manifeſted in</hi> the<note place="margin">Rom. 1. 19.</note> creatures, namely, <hi>his eternall power and Godhead.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:159596:25"/>
            <p>As the exquiſite skill of a workman is diſcerned by his work; ſo is the wiſdome and power of God perſpicuouſly manifeſted <hi>ex operibus,</hi> by his works: Whether you conſider the nature of the heavens, or the influence of the ſtarres, or the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the planets, or the various and terrible me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teors, or the creatures in the aire, earth, or ſeas, how ſtrange they are for forme, how innumerable for multitude; or if you conſider him in one of his moſt excellent and admirable miracles, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the variety of the viſages of ſo many millions of men, not one exactly and in all parts like unto another, which <hi>Plinie</hi> notes, <hi>In facie vultu<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> noſtro</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 10. Hist. Nat.</note> 
               <hi>nullas duas in tot millibus hominum indiſcretas effigies exiſtere, quod ars nulla in paucis numero praeſtet affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctando:</hi> all which are a large Commentary of the divine Eſſence and Wiſdome of Almighty God. And again, that all things ſhould be made of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, <hi>ſolo nutu &amp; verbo, abſque labore,</hi> onely by his command and word, not by any labour; this ſhews his eternall Omnipotency: <hi>Ens ex ente producere eſt potentiae creatae; ens verò. ex non ente, vel ex en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te indiſpoſito eſt potentiae increatae;</hi> which I will En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh thus: To erect a curious fabrick, having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient materials, is the skill of every common ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt; but to erect a curious fabrick, out of baſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials, requires more then ordinary skill: But now, to erect ſo curious a fabrick as is the whole Univerſe, and that out of nothing, onely By ſpeaking the word, <hi>this</hi> needs muſt be <hi>the finger</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 8. 19.</note> 
               <hi>of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, Beloved, have you heard how that God hath left his footſteps imprinted in his works, ſo
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:159596:26"/> that man cannot be altogether without the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God: <hi>In omni re aſpectabili quaedam extant</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vel palpando in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniri poteſt Deus,</hi> Tilen.</note> 
               <hi>Dei vestigia;</hi> in every thing viſible ſome print of Gods footſteps is impreſſible, by which man may (if hee will) track and finde out his Creator, or elſe be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Judge, to pronounce ſentence of condemnation for his wilfull ignorance againſt himſelfe; for God by his works hath left man <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, without all excuſe. In a word, God by his works exhibits himſelfe to a man, to ſee if man will by them ſeek and ſearch after him: <hi>The works of the Lord are great</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>ſought</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 111. 2.</note> 
               <hi>out of all that have pleaſure therein.</hi> So then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light may be taken by viewing God in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>Yet more apparently doth God manifeſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe<note place="margin">By the booke of the Scriptures.</note> to man in the book of the Scriptures. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though then man may ſufficiently reade the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Juſtice, Power, Goodneſſe and Providence of God in the book of the Creatures; yet becauſe for the moſt part hee beholdeth the creatures but ſlightly, and with a glancing eye (for hee ſeldome looks farther into them then they ſtand him in ſtead) very ſeldome hee either ſees or obſerves God in them, (and if hee is purblind in things na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, and ſuch as are obvious to his ſight, no marvell if thick ſcales cloud his eyes concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning things ſupernaturall and ſpirituall.) God therefore, who is abundant in goodneſſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibits himſelfe to man by a farre clearer light, namely, by his word and Sacraments, by which (as through a proſpective) man may diſcern him: and yet every man hath not this glorious privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:159596:26"/> for <hi>Hee hath not dealt ſo with every nation, the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 147. 20.</note> 
               <hi>heathen have no knowledge of his law:</hi> it is onely his Spouſe that can diſcerne him in them; <hi>The natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>man perceiveth not the things of the Spirit.</hi> This peculiar bleſſing wee ſhall apply unto our ſelves by Gods gracious aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>God in his great mercy hath affoorded this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to us, more then to many other people in the world; which argues his wonderfull love that he beareth unto us. Bleſſed be his name, hee hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away the ſcales from our eyes, as hee did from <hi>Sauls</hi> at his converſion, by giving unto us his<note place="margin">Acts 9. 18.</note> word and ſacraments, by which wee may ſee him cleerly, if we will: O pray we then that he would be pleaſed to <hi>annoint</hi> our <hi>eyes with</hi> heavenly <hi>eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalve,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 3. 18.</note> and that hee would give us the eye of true faith, that ſo wee may ſee him in them: for elſe, as the light of the Sun is not diſcerned by a blinde man, although the Sun ſhine never ſo brightly; even ſo this ſupernaturall light in the Scriptures is not ſeen by any who have not the eye of their ſouls opened by faith.</p>
            <p>Some have been ſo Atheiſticall, as to doubt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there were a God or not, and conſequently to deny his word: but when what through the terrors and affrightments of their own conſciences, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the obſervation of the order and gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of all things, they could not deny a ſupreme power; the Divell ſought to delude them by fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that this God was of ſome corporeall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and that hee ſpake unto them by his lying Oracles: by this policie the Divell deluded many, and hindred them the knowledge of the true God.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:159596:27"/>
            <p>Others again grant, that there is a God, and yeeld that hee hath a written word; yet bluſh not blaſphemouſly to ſay, <hi>Meliùs conſultum fuiſſe Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obſervat. Tilen. de orig. ſac. Scrip. Theſ. 35.</note> 
               <hi>ſi nulla unquam extitiſſet Scriptura;</hi> that it had been happier for the Church, if there never had been any Scripture: therefore blaſphemouſly ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it, <hi>Theologiam atramentariam.</hi> Thus impudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly controlling the wiſdome of God, who was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thereby to make himſelfe knowne unto his Spouſe, the Church.</p>
            <p>Another ſort there are, who equall their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written verities in authoritie unto the ſacred Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and moſt groſſely abuſe both the letter and the ſenſe of the Scriptures; thus making the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of man of like authority with the word of God, which was <hi>given by</hi> the <hi>inſpiration</hi> of the<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 16.</note> holy Ghoſt. God hath (bleſſed be his name) mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly preſerved the Scriptures in their genuine puritie, maugre the furie of King <hi>Jehojachim,</hi> who <hi>burnt the roll</hi> that <hi>Baruch</hi> wrote from the mouth of<note place="margin">Jer. 36. 23.</note> the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah:</hi> or maugre the madneſſe of<note place="margin">1 Mac. 1. 56, 57.</note> 
               <hi>Antiochus,</hi> and other tyrants, who ſought utterly to<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro libito mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare, vel adde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, demere quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam.</hi> Craſhaw <hi>on Romes forgeries.</hi>
               </note> aboliſh the books of God extant in their dayes: or maugre the ſacrilegious policy of the Papiſts, who have corrupted it in the text.</p>
            <p>So that if any ſhall now ask, What is meant by the Scriptures? I anſwer, Not mens traditions, nor the unwritten verities of the ſuperſtitious Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, which they equalize with the pure word of God: but thoſe books which are received for (and commonly called) Canonicall, contained in the Old and New Teſtaments, commended unto us from the Prophets and Apoſtles times even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:159596:27"/> now, through the power, providence, and mercy of God; which alſo are <hi>not of any private</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>interpretation: For prophecie came not in old time by the will of man, but holy men ſpake as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt;</hi> and therefore are not to be wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to pleaſe the ſtrange humours and opinions, or to make for the private ends of either Papiſts, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, or Schiſmaticks; much leſſe to be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted in the text by any, but conſtrued according to the true ſenſe and meaning of the holy Ghoſt. Perverters there were of the word of God in the Apoſtles dayes; the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of ſome who wreſted the writings of his beloved brother<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>other Scriptures alſo unto their own deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> I could wiſh there were not ſome ſuch in theſe our dayes: but becauſe there are ſome ſuch, I ſhall advertiſe you in the words of the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>Beware, ſeeing that yee know theſe things before, leſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 17.</note> 
               <hi>ye alſo be led away with the errour of the wicked, and fall from your own ſtedfastneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. But ſome may ſay, <hi>How then ſhall I know that Scripture which is commended unto us, to be the very true word of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The holy Scripture takes not its au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from the penmen who wrote the ſame, for they (for the moſt part) were unlearned men, as ſhepherds, plow-men, fiſher-men, and the like: But the authority of the Scriptures ariſeth,</p>
            <p>Firſt, From the majeſty of him who inſpired the writers to pen things ſo ſublime in ſuch a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar ſtile, and ſimplicity of words: and yet ſuch is the majeſtie of the ſtile, that it is unutterable, being more powerfull in matter, then in words;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:159596:28"/> which none could doe ſave only that God who is cloathed with Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The matter it ſelfe being of that effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy, that <hi>it divideth aſſunder the ſoule and the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 4. 12.</note> 
               <hi>and is a diſcerner of the thoughts and intentions:</hi> as it ſtrikes terrour into the hearts of the greateſt adverſaries that deſpight it; ſo it works an aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from evill, and a converſion to good in them that love it: yea, the comfort that ſome have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in it, hath made them abandon all ſublunary things, and yeeld their lives as a prey into the hands of mercileſſe men, rather then diſclaime it: ſo that, what by convincing and converting, what by affrighting and delighting, all have been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to acknowledge it to be not the invention of mortall man, but the true word of immortall God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The events of the prophecies; as of the promiſed ſeed, the calling of the Gentiles, the deliverance of the Iſraelites from the Egyptian thraldome, &amp;c. How doth <hi>Iſaiah</hi> propheſie of Chriſt to come, as if hee then were already in the fleſh, <hi>Unto us a childe is born,</hi> &amp;c? and the ſame<note place="margin">Iſa. 9. 6.</note> Prophet fore-telleth the freedome of the Jewes from captivity by <hi>Cyrus,</hi> naming him; whereas<note place="margin">Iſa. 45. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Cyrus</hi> was born about 100. yeers after: ſo ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prophet that <hi>cried against the altar at Bethel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 13. 2.</note> named <hi>Joſiah,</hi> and what hee ſhould doe upon that altar; whereas <hi>Joſiah</hi> was born above 300, yeers after. In the New Teſtament S. <hi>Paul</hi> telleth us of <hi>ſeducing ſpirits,</hi> of <hi>doctrines of divels, forbidding to</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4. 1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>marry, and commanding to abſtain from meats, which God hath created to be received with thankſ-giving;</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:159596:28"/> and this is fulfilled in that Antichriſtian Romiſh Church: ſo <hi>Peter</hi> fore-telleth of <hi>ſcoffers, walking</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3. 3.</note> 
               <hi>after their owne luſts;</hi> and have not wee ſome who ſcoffe at Religion, and hate the work of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? I wiſh we had not. Thus the events of the Prophecies prove the truth of the word, to be the word of Truth.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The admirable conſent of the pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, all pointing at the ſame Meſſiah, though li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in ſeverall ages: Adde to this the conſent of the Spirit mentioned by <hi>Paul;</hi> and, ſaith <hi>Peter</hi> in<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 12, 13.</note> the behalf of himſelf and the reſt of the Apoſtles, <hi>Wee have a more ſure word of prophecie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, The wiſdome of God in the penning of his Law: No law of man could ever be ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly deviſed, but ſome offender might finde a ſhift to evade the penaltie of that law: mans law there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore requires to be reviewed and amended; but this law of God remaines as at firſt it was made, and no delinquent can finde the leaſt way to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape the judgement threatned; and this alſo proves it to be the very word of the inviſible God.</p>
            <p>And if any deſire to be ſatisfied yet farther con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Scriptures, whether they are the very word of God, let him doe this; compare Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture by Scripture, and place by place, let the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and the ſenſe goe together, then let him yeeld himſelfe obedient to the Spirit of truth, and that Spirit of truth ſhall witneſſe unto him the truth of the Spirit: and, <hi>let as many as be perfect be thus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 15.</note> 
               <hi>minded: and if in any thing yee be otherwiſe minded, God ſhall reveal even this unto you.</hi> But if any one
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:159596:29"/> will not be content to ſuck the wholeſome milk from the breaſts of the Scriptures, let him conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue ſtill, like the ſwine, to feed upon the husks that he ſo much doth reliſh.</p>
            <p>But as for you (my brethren) of whom I <hi>hope</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 6. 9.</note> 
               <hi>better things, and ſuch as accompany ſalvation, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive</hi> (I humbly beſeech you) <hi>with meekneſſe,</hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie,<note place="margin">James 1. 21.</note> and thankfulneſſe this pure word of God, which is the truth of God, proceeding from the fountaine of Truth it ſelfe, which is onely able to make you wiſe unto ſalvation, and which will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the eyes of your underſtanding cleerly to ſee God: and as for others, no marvell if they never attaine unto the true and perfect knowledge of God, who either know not the Scriptures at all, or elſe, knowing them, ſearch them not diligently, nor reade them with a ſingle eye. Chriſt reproved the Sadduces concerning the reſurrection, <hi>You erre</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>not knowing the Scriptures, nor the power of God:</hi> He reproved alſo the Jews for their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of knowing him, when he proved by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of his Father, of <hi>John,</hi> of his works, and<note place="margin">John 5. 17, 32, 36.</note> of the Scriptures, who hee was; and therefore hee counſelleth them to <hi>ſearch the Scriptures,</hi> for they<note place="margin">Verſ. 39.</note> teſtified of him: <hi>Scrutamini Scripturas.</hi> It was the honour of the Bereans, <hi>in that they received the word</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 17. 11.</note> 
               <hi>with all readineſſe of minde, and ſearched the Scriptures daily whether</hi> the things ſpoken by <hi>Paul were ſo,</hi> or not: and as it was their honour, ſo it will be your bleſſedneſſe to be ſtudious in the Scriptures, which ſo evidently reveal God to you.</p>
            <p>For meditation in the word of God is that key that openeth the door to the cloſet of our hearts,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:159596:29"/> where all our accounts doe lie; it is alſo that looking-glaſſe, or rather that very eye of our ſoul, whereby ſhee ſeeth her ſelfe, and her whole eſtate, and without which ſhee runneth on blindely into a thouſand inconveniences, ſtumbling at every ſtep, being in continuall perill of ſome deadly miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe. And, indeed, the very end why man came into the world was to glorifie God, and ſerve him by meditating on his word: if then wee perform not that ſervice for which wee were created, wee never ſhall receive that reward which is promiſed unto that ſervice. It is true, wicked men build their hope of eternall felicitie on a ſandy founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but this their hope ſhall at laſt make them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed;<note place="margin">Rom. 5. 4.</note> for when their earthy tabernacle ſhall fall, the fall thereof ſhall be great; great (I ſay)<note place="margin">Matth. 7. 27.</note> in reſpect of the change that they ſhall ſee, great for the horrour they ſhall conceive, great for the miſery they ſhall ſuffer, great for the unſpeakable joyes of heaven they ſhall loſe, and great for the eternall and unſupportable pains in hell they ſhall fall into; every way great, elſe the mouth of the Lord would not have ſpoken it. This is the wofull eſtate of the wicked, who deſire not the knowledge of God in his word.</p>
            <p>So now wee know, or may know, that living ill, wee cannot die well, and conſequently, not be ſaved; and wee know, or, at leaſt, ought to know, that many are damned for their ſinnes; and wee know, and cannot chuſe but know, that ſhortly wee muſt die, and receive the wages of our ſinnes, (if unrepented of) namely, eternall death, which is both intolerable and eternall; at
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:159596:30"/> which time ignorance ſhall excuſe none.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, ſith God manifeſteth himſelfe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us more cleerly and apparently in the Scriptures then any other way, let us with heavenly devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſeek him in them, as the Spouſe did her Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved <hi>among the lilies of the field,</hi> and wee ſhall be<note place="margin">Cant. 6. 2.</note> ſure to finde <hi>him whom</hi> our <hi>ſoule loveth,</hi> looking upon us with a raviſhing countenance, even with eyes of delight: and let us with the ears of humble attention liſten to him in his word, in which wee ſhall hear him ſpeaking to us, not in an high hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbolicall ſtraine, but according to our capacitie; and yet again with ſuch ſtupendious majeſtie, that the wiſeſt heathen Philoſopher could never fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thome, and therefore muſt of neceſſitie admire the ſecret and wonderfull wiſdome of him, who hath vouchſafed to deliver in ſuch familiar termes, that which they with greateſt ſcrutinie could never dive into. Hence that gratulation of our Saviour, <hi>Father, I thank thee, that thou haſt hid theſe things</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 11. 25.</note> 
               <hi>from the wiſe and prudent, and haſt revealed them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to babes: even ſo, Father, for ſo it ſeemed good in thy ſight.</hi> Hence alſo is it, that the Scriptures are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <note n="d" place="margin">Ezek. 47. 3, 4, 5.</note> waters, wherein the lamb may wade, and the elephant may ſwim: In them is <note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 5. 12, 13.</note> milk for babes, and ſtrong meat for men of riper yeers: and in<note place="margin">Jer. 2. 13.</note> them God manifeſteth himſelf in all his eſſentiall attributes and properties: O let us <hi>draw, with joy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 12. 3.</note> 
               <hi>waters out of</hi> theſe <hi>wels of ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The attributes and properties of God mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Scriptures are divers, I ſhall only obſerve four.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His Wiſdome: this is profitable to direct us
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:159596:30"/> unto him, and by it wee alſo may grow prudent, and wiſe unto ſalvation. <hi>Wiſdom</hi> (ſaith the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er)<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8. 1.</note> 
               <hi>maketh the face to ſhine;</hi> and not the face alone, but the whole man ſhall be beautified with heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſdome, and this heavenly wiſdome is found in the Scriptures onely; therefore it is called <note n="f" place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 7.</note> 
               <hi>hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den wiſdome,</hi> wiſdome that <note n="g" place="margin">Prov. 1. 7.</note> gives inſtruction: this the <note n="h" place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 20, 21.</note> world underſtandeth not; it is a <note n="i" place="margin">Job 28. 17.</note> jewell of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable worth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His Juſtice; as in puniſhing the wicked, ſo in rewarding the godly: and although ſome are grown ſo cunning, that they can blinde and deceive the eye of mortall man; yet the all-ſeeing eye of Almighty God will finde them out, and his hand will puniſh them: <hi>David</hi> knew full well that God obſerved him at all times and places, when hee ſaith, <hi>O Lord, thou haſt ſearched and known mee, thou</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm 139. 1. ad 14.</note> 
               <hi>knoweſt my down-ſitting, and mine up-riſing, thou un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeſt my thoughts long before: Thou compaſſeſt my path,</hi> &amp;c. And as God eſpieth all our wayes, ſo will hee judge us according to all our works; hee will <hi>bring to judgement every ſecret thing.</hi> O<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12. 14.</note> that men would lay to heart, that hee <hi>that ſeeth in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 6. 4.</note> 
               <hi>ſecret, will reward openly!</hi> But although God can make all things as naked and open to the eye of the world as they are to his own eye (witneſſe the many private murthers, ſecret adulteries, &amp;c.) yet ſome are ſo exceeding vile in their wayes, as if there were neither God to judge them, nor Satan to accuſe them, nor Hell to torment them. <hi>It is a ſhame</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul) even to ſpeake of thoſe things which are done of them in private:</hi> yet although a Chriſtian in modeſtie is aſhamed to ſpeak, they
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:159596:31"/> themſelves bluſh not impudently to act: <hi>The ſhew</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 3. 9.</note> 
               <hi>of their countenance doth witneſſe againſt them, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare their ſin as Sodom, they hide it not: woe unto them, for they have rewarded evill unto themſelves.</hi> The conſideration of this (me thinks) ſhould make all, even incorrigible ſinners, ceaſe to ſin any more, ſith Truth it ſelfe, who cannot lie, hath ſpoken it, that <hi>nothing is ſecret that ſhall not be manifeſt, nor</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 8. 17.</note> 
               <hi>any thing hid that ſhall not be knowne, and come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. His Mercy is manifeſted in the Scriptures: not a Prophet, not a Chapter, ſcarce a Verſe, but ſome wayes or other reflects on his Mercy; yea, <hi>the</hi> whole <hi>earth is full of</hi> his <hi>mercy.</hi> In him <hi>Mercy</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 64. Pſal. 85. 10.</note> 
               <hi>and Truth are met together, Righteouſneſſe and Peace have kiſſed each other. His Mercy reacheth to the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 57. 10.</note> 
               <hi>heavens, and his Truth unto the clouds.</hi> Hee is plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in ſhewing mercy, it is his nature and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie. Of this his Mercy the ſtiffe-necked and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrigible ſinner hath no ſhare, it is onely extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Gods afflicted ones, ſuch as <hi>tremble at his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 66. 2.</note> 
               <hi>word.</hi> Build upon this, In whom there is no fear and knowledge of God, to them there ſhall be no mercy extended from God: It is one of his rich jewels, which hee will not beſtow on ſwine, who never look up unto him; yea, who would under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>value it, and trample it under their feet.</p>
            <p n="4">4. His Providence is manifeſted in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures: <hi>The eyes of all look unto him, and hee giveth</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 145. 15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>them their meat in due ſeaſon: Hee openeth his hand, and ſatisfieth the deſire of every living thing. Job</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting the Providence of God, ſaith, that <hi>hee feedeth the young ravens that call upon him.</hi> If then<note place="margin">Job. 38. 41.</note>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:159596:31"/> God taketh care for ravens, ſure much more will hee provide for thoſe that feare him; hee will ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill their deſire, and in time of adverſitie hee <hi>will heare their cry, and help them.</hi> It was paſt the power of the King of Iſrael to help the woman that cried unto him when Samaria was beſieged, and famine was ſore in the Citie: well might hee ſay, <hi>If the Lord doe not help thee, whence ſhall I help thee,</hi> 2 King. 6. 27. Even Kings themſelves muſt depend on Gods providence for their daily main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance. And although the wicked oft-times have a larger portion of temporall things then the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous; yet God will in a more peculiar way ſo provide for his owne, that in time of dearth they ſhall have enough, when the wicked ſhall ſuffer ſcarcity: <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, Behold, my ſervants</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 65. 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall eate, but yee ſhall be hungry; my ſervants ſhall drink, but yee ſhall be thirſty: behold, my ſervants ſhall rejoyce, but yee ſhall be aſhamed: behold, my ſervants ſhall ſing for joy of heart, but yee ſhall cry for ſorrow of heart, and howl for vexation of ſpirit.</hi> As every ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of a family will provide for his houſhold, yet more eſpecially for his children; ſo will God for his after an eſpeciall manner: hee will provide for them in time of captivitie, as he did for <hi>Jeremiah:</hi> God put it into the heart of King <hi>Nebuchadrezzar</hi> to <hi>give charge concerning</hi> Jeremiah <hi>to the captain of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 39. 12.</note> 
               <hi>the guard, ſaying, Take him, and look well to him, doe him no harme, but do to him even as hee ſhall ſay unto thee.</hi> So alſo for <hi>Ebedmelech: I will deliver thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>ſaith the Lord, and thou ſhalt not be given into the hands of the men of whom thou art afraid. For I will ſurely deliver thee, and thou ſhalt not fall by the ſword, but
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:159596:32"/> thy life ſhall be for a prey unto thee, becauſe thou haſt put thy trust in mee, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Sith then God is thus carefull and provident for us, <hi>let us,</hi> as S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> adviſeth us, <hi>cast all our care upon him, for he careth</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 7.</note> 
               <hi>for us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor doth God provide thus for his owne in things of this life, but hee hath prepared alſo for them eternall habitations; and this is alſo aſſured to us in his word, <hi>I goe</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>to prepare a</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 14. 2.</note> 
               <hi>place for you. In my Fathers houſe are many manſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Feare not, little flock, for it is your Fathers plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 12. 32.</note> 
               <hi>to give you a kingdome:</hi> yea, ſuch a kingdome as never ſhall be ruined. Hee hath provided for them that feare him <hi>an incorruptible inheritance, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 4. &amp; 5. 4.</note> 
               <hi>crowne that fadeth not away.</hi> And in truth, unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, yea, unconceivable are the things which God hath prepared for them that ſet themſelves to ſeek him, to know him, to fear him, and to love him: <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, nor eare heard,</hi> &amp;c. I could<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 9.</note> inſtance more of Gods manifeſtation of himſelfe in other his attributes and properties, out of this book of the Scriptures; but let theſe ſuffice: And come wee now to obſerve how God exhibiteth himſelfe to us by the book of the Scriptures in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thy word</hi> (ſaith the Kingly Prophet) <hi>is a lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horne</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 105.</note> 
               <hi>to my feet, and a light unto my pathes:</hi> a lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horne, to direct us to him in the night of our igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; and a light brightly ſhining on our ſoules, that wee may ſee him. As then, when a man is in the dark, hee knoweth not which way to goe; ſo, when the fogges of our naturall ignorance have darkened our underſtandings, we cannot finde the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:159596:32"/> way that leads unto the heavenly Canaan: God therefore in mercy hath given to us the light of the Scriptures, by which wee may ſee to make ſtraight ſteps thereunto. Wherefore, as when a man hath lain a long time in a darkſome dungeon, or ſome cloſe place where no light hath appeared, at laſt having gained the leaſt benefit of the light of the Sunne, hee rejoyceth; for (ſaith <hi>Solomon) Truely, light is ſweet, and a pleaſant thing it is for a</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 11. 7.</note> 
               <hi>man to behold the Sun:</hi> So ſhould wee ſhew our ſelves joyfull unto the Lord our God, for that when wee were in the darkneſſe of ignorance, and ſhadow of death through unbeliefe, hee was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to vouchſafe, that this glorious light of his word ſhould break forth unto us, and that not for a time onely, and then be clouded again never to ſhine more, but that it ſhould <hi>ſhine forth unto a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John 2. 8.</note> 
               <hi>day;</hi> yea, ſo clearly, that in it wee might ſee God apparently: And although the darkneſſe of Popery hath ſometimes overſhadowed this light<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In the dayes of Queen</hi> Mary.</note> for a time, yet (bleſſed be God) thoſe miſts are diſpelled, maugre the plots of Antichriſtian ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition; and let our hope and prayer be, that thoſe clouds may never obſcure it more. Wherefore, ſith the night is paſt, and the morning-ſtarre hath appeared, let us not any longer ſleep in ſinfull i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnorance; but rather awake, and heare Chriſt in his word, ſaying, <hi>Surge qui dormis, &amp; illuminabit te Chriſtus: Awake thou that ſleepeſt, and ariſe from</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5. 14.</note> 
               <hi>the dead, and Chriſt ſhall give thee light:</hi> and the ſooner, leſt our candleſtick be removed from us. In the dayes of old <hi>Eli, The word of the Lord was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 3. 1.</note> there was no open viſion: the good Lord
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:159596:33"/> grant that the famine of the word may never be known in our land, by our neglect of <hi>caſting off</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 12.</note> 
               <hi>the works of darkneſſe, and putting on the armour of light.</hi> The meditation that <hi>David</hi> had in the word of God, made him to finde, that God was his light and his ſalvation: and certes, in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures is that <hi>light,</hi> of which <hi>David</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>ſown</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 79. 11.</note> 
               <hi>to the righteous, and joyfull gladneſſe to all that are true of heart.</hi> Labour wee then to ſee this light, even God himſelf in the light of the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>That God is light is apparent; <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>God</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 27. 1.</note> 
               <hi>is my light, and my ſalvation:</hi> and Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I am the light of the world, hee that followeth mee ſhall</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 8. 12.</note> 
               <hi>not walk in darkneſſe, but ſhall have the light of life. This is the meſſage that wee have heard of him, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John 1. 5.</note> 
               <hi>unto you, that God is light, and in him is no dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi> Thus God is light. If then wee will follow him, our pathes muſt be light alſo; for, ſaith <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, The path of the juſt is as the ſhining light, that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 4. 18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>ſhineth more and more unto the perfect day. The way of the wicked is darkneſſe, they know not at what they ſtumble. To the Law</hi> then, <hi>and to the Teſtimonie; if</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 8. 20.</note> 
               <hi>they ſpeak not according to this rule, it is becauſe there is no light in them.</hi> In the word onely is that true light to be found, that can beſt direct us to ſee the face of God comfortably ſhining upon our ſouls.</p>
            <p>When ever therefore wee take the ſacred Bible into our hands to reade, in which (as I have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) God moſt brightly looketh upon us, let it be with holy devotion, with reverend intention and attention, ſuppoſing the title of every page to be <hi>Holineſſe to the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 28. 36.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And although there be extant many excellent
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:159596:33"/> books, lively diſcovering Almighty God unto us; yet let us know, that they all borrow their light from the Bible: branches they are of this Vine; ſlips from this Root; ſweet flowers, but gathered out of this Eden of God; ſtreams of wholeſome water, clear as cryſtall, but yet all flowing from this Spring-head: So that I may ſay, that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the book of books, becauſe written by men inſpired <hi>by the holy Ghost,</hi> who is<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 21.</note> the Spirit of truth: and therefore ought not this book to be denied to the people, that they ſhould not ſee God in it; much leſſe, be undervalued, ſlighted, or corrupted by any. And let us know, that the more our ſouls are affected towards God, the more will hee graciouſly manifeſt himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us; even as <hi>David,</hi> whoſe meditation being daily in the law of God, found the light of Gods countenance ſhining more and more upon him, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo-much, that hee earneſtly requeſted God not to turne his face away from him; this alſo was that that made him <hi>wiſer then his teachers.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 99.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Peter</hi> commending the majeſtie of Chriſt at his transfiguration, of which himſelf was an <hi>eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 16.</note> commends alſo the <hi>ſure word of prophecie,</hi> (that is) of preaching the word; and ſaith, that it is <hi>a light ſhining in a dark place, till the day dawne, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 19.</note> 
               <hi>the day-ſtarre appeare in</hi> mens <hi>hearts.</hi> Sith then the miniſtery of the word is a chiefe means to bring this light to our ſoules, let us both heedfully at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it, and highly prize it. What although to the worldly-wiſe it be <hi>accounted fooliſhneſſe;</hi> yet to<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 23.</note> the heavenly-minded it is the joy of their hearts, and <hi>the ſavour of life to ſalvation:</hi> by it God is<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 16.</note>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:159596:34"/> 
               <hi>pleaſed to ſave them that beleeve.</hi> Liſten therefore<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 21.</note> unto it attentively, practiſe it faithfully, and deſpiſe not the meſſage, reſpecting the meanneſſe of the meſſenger, though it be the idle humour of too many to diſtaſte the word preached, becauſe they diſ-eſteeme the preacher; but know, that God is pleaſed by <hi>earthen veſſels</hi> to magnifie his mercy:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 7. Luk. 10. 16.</note> and let the other alſo know, that <hi>whoſoever deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth</hi> us, <hi>deſpiſeth him that ſent</hi> us. If a malefactour, adjudged by the law to die, ſhould refuſe a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pardon, becauſe his enemy brought it, all would condemne him of impudency, and (ſo dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) cenſure him guilty of his own periſhing: But this by the way. Return wee to the obſervation of the benefit which wee receive by the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures.</p>
            <p>The Lord telleth the Jewes, and in them us, that hee had <hi>taught</hi> them <hi>ſtatutes and judgements.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 4. 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>Keep them therefore, and doe them</hi> (ſaith hee;) <hi>for this is your wiſdome and underſtanding in the ſight of the nations, who ſhall ſay, Surely, this great nation is a wiſe and underſtanding people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as daily meditation in the Scriptures brings you neerer unto God, ſo by its illuminating ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue it renders you more heavenly-minded towards God: Pray then as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> adviſeth you, <hi>That <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3. 16.</note> 
               <hi>word of Chriſt may dwell richly in you in all wiſdome and ſpirituall underſtanding,</hi> and not be onely at your fingers ends, nor in your mouthes onely for diſcourſe ſake, nor yet in your hearts only, like a gueſt or tenant, which ſtayeth for a time, and then is gone; but that it may be like a king,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:159596:34"/> dwelling, ruling, and reigning there, as in its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſeat, by the power of his Spirit; even that word which ſo lively ſetteth forth to you him whom <hi>Abraham</hi> fore-ſaw, whom <hi>Jacob</hi> prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied<note place="margin">John 8. 56. Gen. 49. Iſa. 7. 14. Jer. 33. 15. Mal. 4. 2.</note> of, whom <hi>Iſaiah</hi> calleth <hi>Immanuel; Jeremiah, The branch of righteouſneſſe;</hi> and <hi>Malachie, The Sun of righteouſneſſe,</hi> that comes <hi>with healing in his wings:</hi> that that morning-ſtarre may ſhine in your heart which was typified in the old law, but exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited in the new; ſo that what was foretold in the one, is manifeſted in the other: him (I ſay) that you may ſee in the light of the Scriptures by the eye of faith: <hi>ſearch</hi> them then, <hi>for they teſtifie of</hi> him; hee through them, as through windowes, looketh upon you: With <hi>Timothy</hi> know them from your youth, practiſe them in your riper yeers, and let them be your ſtudie in your old age; ſo ſhall you diſcerne ſo much of him, even in this life, through theſe grates, as ſhall even raviſh your ſoules with deſire of a fuller fruition of him hereafter.</p>
            <p>And, as God manifeſteth himſelfe to you in his word, ſo alſo in the bleſſed Sacraments: And firſt, in the Sacrament of Baptiſme, when beleevers are regenerate and born anew of water and the holy Ghoſt, when they are received into the Ark of Chriſts Church, and made lively members of his myſticall body, by remiſſion of their ſinnes, and beſtowing on them his holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, by means whereof they receive ſuch bleſſings from God, as make them to live in him by grace in this life, and aſſure them that they ſhall reigne with him in glory eternally hereafter. Secondly, but moſt cleerly of all, in the Sacrament of the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:159596:35"/> Lords Supper, wherein hee giveth them his fleſh<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Qui fidei ore panem hunc man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducant, ei tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam membra uniantur,</hi> Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len. de Coen. Dom. Theſ. 21.</note> to be their meat, and his bloud to be their drink, imparting to them that heavenly hidden Manna, which they take by the hand, and eat by the mouth of faith. Every true ſpouſe of Chriſt in this ſeeth his ſuper-abundant love, in that hee was pleaſed to vaile his glorious Divinitie with the mantle of our infirme mortalitie, that ſo he might more eaſily make himſelfe known unto us. For as hee is God co-equall with his Father, hee is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible; but as hee in great humility aſſumed our nature (<hi>per operationem</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) by making himſelf in forme of a ſervant, who was Lord of all, (for hee did onely (<hi>majeſtatem ſeponere, non deponere</hi>) for a while lay aſide his majeſty, not quite diſrobe himſelfe of it) hee was viſible amongſt men, hee was converſant with men, hee did eate, drink, ſleep, talk, and at laſt ſuffered death by men; every way hee did communicate himſelfe unto men, making the faithfull one with him by ſpirituall union and conjunction. Hence is that ſaying, <hi>Paries eſt verbi</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cornel. à Lap.</note> 
               <hi>incarnati humanitas, per quam ſtans, quaſi per feneſtras proſpicit in Eccleſiam &amp; fideles, unde &amp; nos aſpicimus Deitatem per humanitatem.</hi> Theſe are the windows through which Chriſt, manifeſting himſelfe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veales himſelfe unto us, and in them declaring the ſecret will and work of God concerning our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and ſalvation; whereof, except he were perfect God, hee could have no knowledge: for none, being meer and onely man, could ever have ſearched out that bottomleſſe abyſſe, nor ever have found out ſo intricate a myſtery.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, God maketh himſelfe knowne unto<note place="margin">By the book of Conſcience.</note>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:159596:35"/> man by the book of Conſcience: for there is none ſo atheiſticall, but the terrours of his Conſcience will make him acknowledge a Deity.</p>
            <p>Conſcience is a practicall ſyllogiſme condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſcientia est ſyllogiſmus pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticus ex lege,</hi> Urſin.</note> man for the breach of Gods law; the Major whereof is the letter of the law, <hi>Curſed is every man that continueth not in all things which are written in the book of the law to doe them:</hi> The Minor is the accuſing of Conſcience, <hi>But I have broken the law:</hi> Hence the Concluſion neceſſarily muſt follow, <hi>Therefore I am accurſed.</hi> Sometimes it is put for the ſpirit or ſoule of a man, and ſometimes for the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of the ſoule; ſo wee reade, that the law of God is written in our hearts, our <hi>conſciences either</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 15.</note> 
               <hi>accuſing or excuſing:</hi> which muſt be underſtood (<hi>in intellectu nostro</hi>) in the underſtanding facultie of the ſoule; and in this ſenſe, the majeſtie and power of God ſhineth even to the conſciences of the heathen and infidels: <hi>Non omnis Numinis ſenſu</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tilen.</note> 
               <hi>carent, qui in ſylvis oberrantes, ferinam agunt vitam:</hi> Even they who live like ſavage beaſts in woods, are not altogether void and ſenſeleſſe of a ſupreme power: and whence is this but from the inward curb of conſcience?</p>
            <p>Yet more eſpecially and cleerly God is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted to the conſciences of men theſe two wayes:</p>
            <p n="1">1. By the miniſtery of the word, by which hee powerfully worketh on their conſciences.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By the inward checks of conſcience after ſin committed, both in the godly, and alſo in the wicked.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by the miniſtery of the word; and this is four wayes:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:159596:36"/>1. By opening that which was before lock'd up: The cloſets of mens hearts are lock'd up by ſin and ignorance, ſo that they cannot rightly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of God as they ought, untill hee who hath <hi>the key of David</hi> be pleaſed to open them by the<note place="margin">Revel. 3. 7.</note> miniſtery of the word: the heart of man naturally being like unto a ſpring-lock, which ſhutteth of its own accord, but cannot be opened without a key. Thus God is ſaid to open the heart of <hi>Lydia,</hi> when<note place="margin">Acts 16. 14.</note> ſhee heard the word of God from the mouth of <hi>Paul,</hi> and by the ſame means to convert the Jay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler<note place="margin">Verſ. 31.</note> and his houſhold; ſo alſo God opened the hearts of three thouſand at <hi>Peters</hi> preaching. God<note place="margin">Acts 2.</note> hath committed the keyes of his kingdom unto the Miniſters of his Goſpel, whereby he enables them<note place="margin">Matth. 16. 19.</note> to ſpeak unto his people; yet, <hi>Spiritus ſanctus est, qui verbi praeconio hominum mentes illuminat, qui au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res perforat, &amp; qui corda aperit, ut Scripturae tanquam divinae firmiter aſſentiantur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. By ſoftning that which before was hard: The heart of man naturally is <note n="*" place="margin">Ezek. 11. 19.</note> flinty, God only (ſaith <hi>Job</hi>) can ſoften it; and this God worketh<note place="margin">Job 23. 16.</note> by his word. Thus, when <hi>Joſiah</hi> heard the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments<note place="margin">2 King. 22. 19.</note> of God threatned againſt the Jews, he grew tender-hearted: O that the word of God might work the like effect on us, even now, when not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his threatnings are denounced, but his hand is alſo heavie upon us! But, alas! we have too many that <hi>refuſe to hearken,</hi> that <hi>pull away the ſhoulder, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zech. 7. 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>ſtop the eare, that they might not heare: Yea, they make their hearts as an adamant ſtone, leſt they ſhould hear the law, and the words which the Lord of hoſts hath ſent in his Spirit by the former Prophets; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:159596:36"/> hath there come great wrath from the Lord of hoſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. God revealeth himſelfe to man by the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of the word in convincing the conſcience for ſinne, which was before as it were ſeared up: Thus dealt hee with Ephraim, <hi>After Ephraim was</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 31. 19.</note> 
               <hi>inſtructed, hee ſmote upon his thigh, hee was aſhamed, and even confounded, becauſe hee did bear the reproach of his youth.</hi> Thus <hi>Agrippa</hi> could not but be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed in conſcience of the Deitie of Chriſt by the preaching of <hi>Paul,</hi> when hee ſaid, <hi>Almoſt thou per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadeſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 26. 28.</note> 
               <hi>me to be a Chriſtian:</hi> ſuch a victorious grace of wiſdome hath the holy Ghoſt infuſed into the miniſtery of the word. <hi>Felix</hi> alſo could not but be convicted in his conſcience of the dreadfull juſtice of God, when hee <hi>trembled,</hi> hearing <hi>Pauls</hi> diſcourſe<note place="margin">Acts 24. 25.</note> concerning the torments of hell, <hi>and judgement to come:</hi> Happy had it been for them both, if they had fully aſſented to the power of his preaching. <hi>Tanta eſt Scripturae vis, ut etiam hoſtibus ſuis verum</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tilen.</note> 
               <hi>teſtimonium exprimat, &amp; in tenebrionum latibula ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorem aliquem immittat; nimirum ut liquidò conſtet, internam eſſe hujus lucis proprietatem, ex ſe, &amp; per ſe exiſtere:</hi> Such is the power of the Scripture, that it gives evident teſtimony of its truth, even to its very enemies, and ſends forth its beams of light into the ſecrets of the craftieſt plotters, that it may manifeſtly appear, that it is the propertie of the Scriptures to work inwardly on the conſcience, by ſhining of it ſelf, and in it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By the miniſtery of the word God <hi>purgeth the conſcience from dead works, to ſerve the living God:</hi> The word doth metamorphoſe a man, and makes
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:159596:37"/> him to be other then what hee was before: thus <hi>Paul,</hi> after that he was converted, exerciſed himſelf<note place="margin">Acts 24. 16.</note> 
               <hi>to have a conſcience void of offence both towards God, and towards man.</hi> At firſt <hi>Paul</hi> thought to have do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineered over the poor Chriſtians at Damaſcus, but after he had ſeen the Lord Chriſt in the midſt of that glorious light, which exceeded the light of the Sun, hee was content to ſit (as it were) at the feet of <hi>Ananias,</hi> and be inſtructed by him. Now,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lupus hic Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin ovi caput ſubmiſit,</hi> Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. Epiſt. 3. Note. <hi>Aug. de Doctr. Chriſt. proleg.</hi>
               </note> if hee that was ſuch an eminent Apoſtle, yea, who heard Chriſt himſelfe from heaven, muſt receive inſtruction from another; how dare any man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe even the meaneſt of Gods Miniſters? Nor was this converſion of the Apoſtle without ſome ſpeciall ſignification; for hereby is ſhewed, that they which are truely converted, are alſo ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually inlightned: they are made blinde to world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, and the eyes of their mindes are onely taken up with the beholding of things heavenly; and the bent of their affections is, <hi>to hold the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3. 9.</note> 
               <hi>of faith in a pure conſcience.</hi> To conclude this point; Happy is hee, who when God ſpeaketh to his conſcience by the miniſtery of the word, (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be for peace, or for warre) receiveth it with an honeſt and good heart, and is ready to ſay as once <hi>David</hi> did to <hi>Abigail,</hi> when ſhe met him, <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25. 32.</note> 
               <hi>be the Lord God of Iſrael, which hath ſent thee this day to meet mee, and bleſſed be thine advice:</hi> ſo they, Bleſſed be the Lord, who hath ſent thee this day to ſpeak home to my conſcience, and bleſſed be thine inſtructions, which make mee to look back to him from whom I was, like a prodigall, eſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Thus much concerning Gods manifeſting
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:159596:37"/> himſelfe to the conſcience by the miniſtery of the word.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God manifeſteth himſelf to man by the checks of conſcience after ſin committed; and thus both to the godly, and to the wicked.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to the godly: What was it that made <hi>Adam</hi> hide himſelf <hi>from the preſence of God,</hi> but the<note place="margin">Gen. 3. 8.</note> check of his conſcience for the guilt of his ſin in eating the forbidden fruit? The check of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is called the ſmiting of the heart; ſo we reade, that when David had cut off the skirt of <hi>Sauls</hi> gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 24. 5.</note> 
               <hi>his heart ſmote him;</hi> that is, his conſcience checkt him: The like ſmiting <hi>David</hi> had after his<note place="margin">2 Sam. 24. 10.</note> numbring of the people. And to this end doth God reprove man by the check of his own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, even to awaken him from ſin, leſt hee ſleep the ſleep unto death. The Prophet complains, that <hi>there</hi> was <hi>no reſt in</hi> his <hi>bones by reaſon of</hi> his <hi>ſins:</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till<note place="margin">Pſal. 32. 3.</note> his heart was purged from ſin, hee could feel no reſt within his ſoule; for conſcience is a part of the underſtanding, determining all actions ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with or againſt; it either accuſeth man for good omitted, or evill committed, or elſe excuſeth him, in aſſurance that his perſon is accepted as righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous before God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to the wicked: For there is none ſo notoriouſly wicked in committing any villany, but hee hath ſometimes a ſting wounding his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and telling him of a ſupreme and juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venger; ſometimes his heart ſmites him, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles him, though but for a time; and though not for effectuall converſion, yet ſome gripings there are, ſuch as <hi>Cain, Ahab, Belſhazzar,</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> had:
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:159596:38"/> theſe (I ſay) laſted but for a time; for the Preacher obſerveth, that <hi>becauſe ſentence againſt an evill work</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8. 11.</note> 
               <hi>is not executed ſpeedily, therefore the hearts of the ſons of men is fully ſet in them to doe evill:</hi> Yet in all, both in good and bad, Conſcience will doe her duty; for ſhee is like the poiſe of a clock, which, being wound up, ſets all the wheeles a going: even ſo Conſcience, being wound up by the hand of Gods juſtice, ſets all the members on work, makes the tongue confeſſe, the eyes weep, the heart throb, the knees ſmite one againſt another, the fiſt ſtrikes upon the breſt, no part but acts its part. And now (Beloved) judge, when the conſcience of a man findes that ſhee hath to deale with an angry God,<note place="margin">Job 13. 26.</note> one that <hi>writes</hi> (as <hi>Job</hi> complaines) <hi>bitter things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 139. 7.</note> her, and that ſhee knowes not where to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take her ſelfe (for to <hi>flee from</hi> his <hi>preſence</hi> ſhee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not) how ſhee is perplexed: eſpecially, if ſhe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not feele God reconciled unto her, and herſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God. No marvell that <hi>David mourned through the diſquietneſſe of</hi> his <hi>heart,</hi> ſaying to God, <hi>Thou</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 30. 7.</note> 
               <hi>hiddeſt thy face, and I was troubled.</hi> To a deep ſenſe<note place="margin">Matth. 26. 75.</note> of miſery was <hi>Peter</hi> brought after hee had denyed his Lord, and forſwore his Chriſt, till his Maſter, looking back upon him, brought to his remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance his by-paſt ſin; then <hi>went he out, and wept bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly.</hi> And to ſuch a ſenſe of reſtleſneſſe was <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 27. 3, 4, 5.</note> brought after hee had betrayed his Maſter, though hee found not the like comfort as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did: On ſome, the horrour of conſcience works repentance unto ſalvation; whereas it drives others to the gulfe of deſpaire.</p>
            <p>Certes, it was not without divine providence,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:159596:38"/> that the very heathen termed the terrours of a wicked conſcience <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſearcher out, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſher of ſin; ſometimes called <hi>Furiae,</hi> the furies of hell, or worm of conſcience; ſometimes alſo called <hi>Intemperiae,</hi> the tortures of the minde; and ſometimes (<hi>per <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) Eumenides,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Acheron</hi> and <hi>Nox,</hi> that is, Hell and Darkneſſe; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by<note place="margin">Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d minimè ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> benignae.</note> inſinuating the wofull bitterneſſe, and extreme horrour wherewith the wicked are perplexed: And if the heathen ſtiled them by ſuch horrid termes, how ſhould we dread to harbour in us ſuch ſnakes?</p>
            <p>And our Saviour tels us of an unquenchable fire, ſo alſo of a never-dying worm: ſuch a worm there is of conſcience; and it is ſo called, becauſe, as a worme lyeth eating and gnawing that wood in which ſhee abideth: ſo the worm of conſcience, lying within us, gripeth and tormenteth us, by bringing to our memories all the cauſes of preſent and future calamities; as our wilfull negligences whereby wee loſt our firſt enjoyed felicities, at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of which conſiderations ſhe giveth us a dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly griping; as alſo all our occaſions offered to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape thoſe miſeries in which wee are now plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; adde to theſe all thoſe opportunities for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming that glory which we have now hazzard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; as alſo how ungraciouſly wee have quenched the good motions of Gods holy Spirit, by which wee might have been reclaimed: adde further, how vain thoſe worldly trifles are, which we have too eagerly followed; and laſtly, how wee our ſelves are become worldly fooles, and others ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually wiſe, whereas we dream'd otherwiſe.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:159596:39"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:159596:39"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:159596:40"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:159596:40"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:159596:41"/>
            <p>From whence wee may obſerve, that <hi>A ſecure ſinner is an enemy unto himſelfe;</hi> for if there be no fulneſſe of joy but in the preſence of God, then certes, in a wofull condition are they, who, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in their ſins againſt the curb of conſcience, deprive themſelves of this happineſſe.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee that an accuſing conſcience mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſteth a Deity, and that the law of God is written<note place="margin">Rom. 2. 15.</note> in the hearts of men. You ſee alſo that both good and bad have ſometimes theſe checks of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which, like that voice mentioned by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> calleth to them, ſaying, <hi>This is the way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 3. 21.</note> 
               <hi>walk in it, when they turn to the right hand, or when they turn to the left;</hi> pointing out another way then what they formerly trod awry in: to which voice of conſcience, if men will liſten and obey, then ſhall it goe well with them; for they ſhall not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know that there is a God, but they ſhall in ſome meaſure ſee him, and be acquainted with him: but if they ſhall harden their hearts, and labour to <hi>quench the good ſpirit of God,</hi> which at that time<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5. 19. Revel. 3. 20.</note> knocks at the door of their hearts, and ſeeks ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for their ſalvation, then are they guilty of their own damnation.</p>
            <p>Wouldeſt thou, O man, then know whether thou art a childe of God, or not? know then that there is a conſcience,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Good, yet not quiet; and this is in the godly, when they are reſtleſſe in themſelves for ſins as yet unrepented of: Thus was it with that kingly Prophet <hi>David</hi> after his committing of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and adultery; how doth hee, in perplexitie of his ſoul, being awakened by the Prophet <hi>Nathan,</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:159596:41"/> cry out, that God would, <hi>according to the multitude</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51. 1.</note> 
               <hi>of</hi> his <hi>tender mercies, blot out</hi> his <hi>tranſgreſsions,</hi> &amp;c. So alſo when God had laid his hand heavie upon him, how doth hee mourn? <hi>There is no ſoundneſſe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 38. 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>in my fleſh becauſe of thine anger, neither is there any peace in my bones by reaſon of my ſin: For mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities are gone over mine head; as an heavie burden, they are too heavie for mee.</hi> The ſickneſſe of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy put him in minde of the ſin of his ſoule; that which hee did endure, did put him in minde of what hee did deſerve, which galled his conſcience with the remembrance of his particular ſlips and failings, both by omiſſion and commiſſion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, There is a conſcience quiet, yet not good; and this is in the wicked: as namely, when after ſin committed, their hearts remain ſtill ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durate, cauterized, ſenſeleſſe: they ſleep ſo ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſin, that they never feele the ſting of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence wounding them; they are ſo delighted in ſin, that they never regard when they ſin, nor how they ſin, nor againſt whom they ſin, nor before whom they ſin: <hi>The ſhew of their countenance doth</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 3. 9.</note> 
               <hi>testifie againſt them, they declare their ſin as Sodom, they hide it not; therefore wo to their ſouls, for they have rewarded evill unto themſelves.</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> excellently decyphereth them; <hi>They have their underſtanding</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>darkned, being alienated from the life of God through the ignorance that is in them, becauſe of the blindneſſe of their heart: Who being paſt feeling, have given themſelves over unto laſciviouſneſſe, to work all unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with greedineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, There is a conſcience both good, and quiet; and this is proper onely to the elect: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:159596:42"/> when God ſpeaks peace to their ſoules, by aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring them of the free pardon of all their ſinnes, and the Spirit of God teſtifies to their ſpirits, that they are the ſonnes of God, and ſhall be made partakers of life everlaſting in the heavenly Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, There is a conſcience neither good, nor quiet; and this accompanieth onely the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate: namely, when through ſenſe of ſin, hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of conſcience, and Gods wrathfull, yet juſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, ſuch a dreadfull trembling ſeizeth on them, that they know not where to betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. From this perplexity no incorrigible ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner can exempt himſelfe; neither Kings, nor great<note place="margin">Rev. 6. 15. ad finem.</note> men, nor rich men, nor mighty men, nor bond, nor free men.</p>
            <p>According to theſe obſervations examine thou thy ſelfe, and thou ſhalt eaſily finde whether thou belongeſt to God or not: And if thy conſcience hath wounded thee, ſo that thou canſt without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny flattery aſſure thy ſelfe that thou haſt through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repented thee of all thoſe ſins, which, like <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charia's</hi> talent of lead on the mouth of the ephah,<note place="margin">Zech. 5. 7, 8.</note> preſſed thee even to the pit of hell, and that thou findeſt God to be a reconciled God to thee in the face of his Son; then is thy condition happy, and the brightneſſe of Gods countenance hath ſhined upon thee: otherwiſe, if thou wert never ſenſible of thy ſins, nor haſt yeelded to the checks of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; then is it an evident ſigne, that if ever thou didſt confeſſe thy ſins, yet it was but a meer orall confeſſion, hypocritically performed, and ſo thy condition is moſt miſerable.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:159596:42"/>
            <p>And now (Beloved) conceive within your ſelves what an horrour it is to have an accuſing and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting conſcience alwayes purſuing a ſinner; nay, not onely purſuing him, but alwayes harbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his breſt, like an <hi>Erynnis, quae indagatrix eſt graviſsimorum flagitiorum,</hi> which is the Inquiſitor, and hunter out of the groſſeſt crimes, to be his boſome companion, and yet alwayes pleading guiltie, ſo that the ſinner ſhall not know where to repoſe himſelfe for feare; the very ſhaking of a leafe ſhall make him to tremble, and be at his wits end: Such a comrade had that fratricide <hi>Cain,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hee had ſpilt his brothers bloud, when he ſaid, <hi>Behold, thou haſt driven mee out this day from the face</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 14.</note> 
               <hi>of the earth, and from thy face ſhall I be hid, and I ſhall be a fugitive and a vagabond in the earth: and it ſhall come to paſſe, that every one that findeth mee ſhall ſlay mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſting of death is ſin,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul;</hi> yea, and the ſting of conſcience is ſin alſo, which ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verwhelms ſome with an horrible dread, that they <hi>flee when none purſueth.</hi> It is the nature of ſin to<note place="margin">Pro. 28. 1.</note> purſue the ſinner, and <hi>a wounded conſcience who can</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 18. 4.</note> 
               <hi>beare? Moſes</hi> told the Iſraelites, that they ſhould be ſure, that if they ſinned againſt the Lord, their <hi>ſin</hi> would <hi>finde them out:</hi> and, <hi>Evill purſueth the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 32. 23<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Pro. 13. 21.</note> ſaith <hi>Solomon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, although God ſpeaketh thus to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of the wicked; yea, although the ſting of conſcience doth (as it were) make their <hi>ears to tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 3. 11. 2 King. 21. 12.</note> as the Lord ſpeaks: although it awakens them by ſounding an alarm of Gods judgements in their ears, yet <hi>veternum excutere nolunt:</hi> they will
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:159596:43"/> not be rouſed from their ſottiſhneſſe, but, with <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons</hi> fool, <hi>A little more ſleep, a little more ſlumber,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 6. 10.</note> a little longer basking in ſin, till at laſt that grim ſergeant Death arreſts them, and layes them in the priſon of the grave, there to remain till the great and generall Aſſizes.</p>
            <p>This evidently appeares, in that they labour to quiet and appeaſe the gnawings of this worm of conſcience, then whoſe bite nothing ſmarts more, then whoſe ſting nothing galls more, and then whoſe torment nothing frets more; and yet they fain would huſh and ſtill it, that it may not affright and appall them. But conſcience will not be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted; but as ſhee keeps a true regiſter of all ſins, ſo ſhee gives in a true evidence againſt all ſinnes. Doe the wicked what they can, God hath ſaid that their worm ſhall never die, and that <hi>no peace</hi> ſhall<note place="margin">Mark 9. 44. Iſa. 57. 20.</note> be <hi>to the wicked, but they</hi> ſhall be <hi>like the raging ſea, whoſe waters caſt up mire and dirt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Adde to theſe inward torments of the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, thoſe outward plagues by which God <hi>ſhall</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 2. 5.</note> 
               <hi>vexe them in his ſore diſpleaſure,</hi> and by which at laſt they ſhall be enforced to confeſſe him juſt, whom willingly they would not acknowledge to be at all. Wherefore, Beloved, labour to gain a quiet, yet a tender conſcience, which, as it is a continuall feaſt; ſo it is a moſt delightſome garden to ſolace a mans ſoule in; it is the Exchequer of the King of kings, in which hee keepeth the audit of all his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts; it is the high Court of the great God, and the habitation of the holy Ghoſt: and think not to beguile conſcience, or to delude Gods all-ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eye; for the one will be an upright witneſſe,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:159596:43"/> the other a ſevere Judge. I conclude this point with that obſervation of <hi>Tilenus: In calamitates magnas incident, qui vel ſubdoli ingenii ſtrophis, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtratûs cognitionem eluſerant; vel virium fiduciâ, perruptis legum clathris, Judicum ſubſellia contempſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant: ad ineluctabile enim tribunal ſummi Judicis pertrahentur, qui nec fraude eludetur, nec vi ſuperari poterit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I at large declared how God is pleaſed to manifeſt himſelfe to the conſciences of men both by the miniſtery of the word, and alſo by the checks of the ſame. In a word, take as a Corrolary the ſumme of all; God is pleaſed to exhibite himſelfe to all our ſenſes: Thus wee ſee him in the admirable fabrick of the world, and varietie of creatures: Thus wee hear him in his word preached: Thus wee taſte him in the fruits of the earth carnally; but ſpiritually in the bleſſed Sacrament: Thus wee ſmell him in the fragrancy of his graces: And thus wee feel him in the checks of our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; our outward ſenſes being the grates or win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of our ſoules, nothing being conveyed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the one, but by the other: Wee underſtand no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, we know nothing, but either the ear, or the eye, or ſome other ſenſe muſt firſt preſent it to the ſoule. As then many windowes yeeld more light into a roome; ſo the more ſenſes there are that preſent a matter to the ſoule, the more cleerly doth the ſoul underſtand it, and conceive it. Theſe (Beloved) are the windowes, grates, and latteſſes thorow which Chriſt looketh upon his Spouſe, the Church: Yet, as followeth in my third Generall,</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:159596:44"/>
            <p>It is but hieroglyphically, enigmatically, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely.</p>
            <p>The Egyptians uſed to expreſſe themſelves by myſticall cyphers; and when Almighty God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to <hi>Moſes,</hi> it was either in <hi>fire,</hi> or elſe in a<note place="margin">Exod. 3. 6.</note> 
               <hi>cloud,</hi> in both which, to the eye of <hi>Moſes,</hi> it was<note place="margin">Cap. 40. 34.</note> obſcurely: So when the Lord appeared to <hi>Elijah,</hi> it was by a <hi>voice,</hi> which is audible, not viſible:<note place="margin">1 King. 19.</note> When Chriſt was transfigured upon the Mount, it<note place="margin">Mark 9. 3.</note> was in ſuch a brightneſſe, that the Apoſtles could not endure to behold the glory of his Majeſtie. So that although God is every-where about us, yet ſuch is our dimneſſe, wee cannot perceive him: like the ſervant of <hi>Eliſha,</hi> wee are blinde, and ſee<note place="margin">2 Kin. 6. 16, 17.</note> not God neer us, unleſſe God in mercy open our eyes, as hee did his. The book of the Creatures, the book of the Scriptures, and the book of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience may ſerve us in ſome ſtead; yet are but as dark ſhadowes, glimeringly ſetting forth him who is light inviſible: They may ſerve as a candle in the night; but as when the light of the Sun ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, the light of the candle is darkened: ſo when our vaile of mortality is put away, wee ſhall ſee God more perfectly.</p>
            <p>In the Scriptures we read of a four-fold light.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Light is taken properly, as of the Sun, Moon, and Starres, which give light to all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures<note place="margin">Gen. 1. 14, &amp;c.</note> upon the earth: to this end they were crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Light is taken figuratively; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for God himſelfe, <hi>God is light:</hi> ſometimes<note place="margin">1 John 1. 5.</note> for Gods countenance; ſo <hi>David</hi> prayeth God to <hi>lift up the light of</hi> his <hi>countenance upon</hi> him: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times<note place="margin">Pſal. 4. 6.</note>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:159596:44"/> it is taken for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> for true<note place="margin">Luk. 2. 32. Matth. 5. 14.</note> 
               <hi>beleevers;</hi> or it may be taken for the light of Gods Spirit, with which ſome were endued in the dayes<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5. 8.</note> of the Apoſtles, for the diſcerning of thoſe who ſpake by the Spirit of God, from thoſe who ſpake by a falſe ſpirit; therefore it was called <hi>the gift of</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12. 10.</note> 
               <hi>diſcerning of ſpirits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Light is taken for the light of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, leading us to God; <hi>Thy word is a lanthorne</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 105.</note> 
               <hi>to my feet, and a light unto my pathes:</hi> for naturally our underſtandings are darke, onely God in mercy revealeth himſelf unto us by the light of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures: Hence is it, that wee are adviſed both by that Evangelicall Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> as alſo that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Apoſtle <hi>John,</hi> to <hi>walke in the light of the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 2. 5. 1 John 1. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Light is taken for comfort after the troubleſome ſtormes of affliction: ſo the Prophet <hi>Micah, Rejoyce not againſt mee, O mine enemy: When</hi>
               <note place="margin">Micah 7. 8.</note> 
               <hi>I fall, I ſhall riſe; when I ſit in darkneſſe, the Lord ſhall be a light unto me.</hi> When <hi>Hamans</hi> plot was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated, <hi>The Jewes had light and gladneſſe, joy and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſth. 8. 16.</note> and ſaith <hi>David, Light is ſowne for the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 97. 11.</note> 
               <hi>and joyfull gladneſſe to them that are true of heart.</hi> Hence is it that the Prophet <hi>Iſaich</hi> comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Church in the uberity of her children, by the promulgation of the Goſpel; <hi>Ariſe, be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 60. 1.</note> 
               <hi>for thy light cometh, and the glory of the Lord is riſen upon thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe lights makes not for our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, the three later may help us very much. If therefore the Spirit of God ſhineth upon our ſouls, it will clear our underſtandings to diſcerne God
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:159596:45"/> in the light of the Scriptures; and if wee can ſee God in the light of the Scriptures, wee ſhall be ſure to attain to the light of ſaving comfort, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the latter dependeth on the former: Thus the Eunuch, although his devotion led him to<note place="margin">Act. 8. 30, &amp;c.</note> read the Scriptures, yet did hee not underſtand all that hee did read, till the Spirit ſent <hi>Philip</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it unto him, then went hee away rejoycing. Nor was it (ſaith <hi>Calvin</hi>) unprofitable for him to<note place="margin">Calvin.</note> exerciſe his minde in places of Scripture more obſcure, becauſe by ſearching and ſtudying there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the ſenſe of them, through the aſſiſtance of Gods Spirit, is to be attained unto. And by the way, Note the blinde condition of the Romiſh<note place="margin">Note.</note> Laitie, who ſatisfie themſelves with imbracing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny doctrines of their Church, without ſearching the grounds thereof from the Scriptures, taking all upon the truſt of others, and being content to goe without examining them by that touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone.</p>
            <p>But, to proceed, Our knowledge of God in this life is in part, that is, is imperfect, as the beholding of a man ſuddenly paſſing by, whoſe back-parts onely wee can look upon: our more fuller know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God is reſerved untill that time, in which we ſhall be made like unto him: <hi>When wee all, with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3. 18.</note> 
               <hi>face, beholding as in a glaſſe the glory of the Lord, ſhall be transformed into the ſame image, from glory to glory, even as by the Spirit of the Lord.</hi> The bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this knowledge breaks forth in this life, when of ſinners wee are made righteous by juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; but attains not to its perfect heighth till wee are transformed into that image. Thus wee
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:159596:45"/> paſſe from the glory of creation, to the glory of juſtification; and from the glory of being the ſons of God, to the glory of being like unto God. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding hereunto is that of S. <hi>John, Beloved, wee are</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John 3. 2.</note> 
               <hi>now the ſons of God, yet it doth not appeare what wee ſhall be: but wee know, that when hee ſhall appear, wee ſhall be like him; for wee ſhall ſee him as hee is.</hi> In this life wee cannot, in the life to come wee ſhall receive the endowments of perfect beatitude, both in ſoule and body. Here wee may onely conceive him with the eyes of our mindes, but then we ſhall perceive him with the eyes of our bodies; <hi>Even with theſe ſame eyes</hi> (ſaith <hi>Job:</hi>) onely wee muſt<note place="margin">Job 19. 26, 27.</note> grant, that corruption muſt firſt put on incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for <hi>Fleſh and bloud cannot inherit the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 50.</note> 
               <hi>of God.</hi> Our bodies ſhall not then be earthy, animated onely by a ſoule, and ſeparable from them, as now they are; but ſpirituall, all danger and cauſe of ſeparation being done away by the Spirit of Chriſt quickning us. Nor yet may wee, with <hi>Origen,</hi> ſuppoſe that our bodies ſhall be aeriall, and not conſiſt of fleſh and bones; this repugneth <hi>Jobs</hi> confeſſion: and our Saviours body after his reſurrection was not a ſpirit, <hi>for</hi> that <hi>hath not fleſh and bones,</hi> as his bodie had, which is<note place="margin">Luk. 24. 39.</note> an aſſurance that our very bodies ſhall riſe again, though not fraile, as now they are; but, as <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. epiſt. 145. ad Conſent.</note> ſheweth, they ſhall be ſpirituall; not that the fleſh ſhall be aboliſhed, but ſpirituall, becauſe fully guided by the ſpirit, and vivified to a life, being without all ſuſtenance, never to have end. And reaſon there is, why this our corruption ſhould put on incorruption; for how elſe can
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:159596:46"/> wee enjoy the <hi>incorruptible crowne of glory?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>By conſequence therefore it muſt follow, that whileſt wee are clothed with corruptible clay, <hi>Ex parte tantùm cognoſcimus, modicum ex multo; Wee know but in part,</hi> and alas, leſſe then wee ought; wee are not able to diſcern the pure and perfect vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Deity. Whileſt we live in theſe earthy tabernacles, our primeſt knowledge of God in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his incomprehenſible Eſſence, is like the knowledge of a childe to a man of riper yeeres, weak and tender; for children have not <hi>ſapienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ad ſenſum,</hi> knowledge according to diſcretion. The perfecteſt light that wee have of God in this life may well be compared to a kingdom deſcryed by a ſmall land-skip, here a citie, there a caſtle; here a village, there a mountain; here a forreſt, there a river; here beaſts, there men; all which are done with very little touches, to repreſent greater bodies: Even ſo our beſt knowledge of God is clouded and imperfect, and our brighteſt ſpeculation admits of much weakneſſe and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, of many fogs and miſts; yea, our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in Theologie, and Divine myſteries is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, and in part, <hi>quia fide nititur,</hi> becauſe it is built upon faith: now that which reaſon cannot appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, faith doth beleeve; <hi>ideo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ex parte tantùm eſt ſcientia,</hi> our knowledge therefore muſt needs be in part, <hi>faith</hi> being <hi>the evidence of things not ſeen: Wee ſee</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>ſed per ſpeculum, as through a</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 12.</note> 
               <hi>glaſſe, darkly;</hi> our knowledge at the beſt being like dim-ſighted eyes, which ſee ſomewhat indeed of God through the glaſſe of the creatures, and Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures; or at the moſt, by ſimilitudes and figures,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:159596:46"/> by which God exhibiteth himſelfe to ſuch as are moſt in favour with him, as to the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 2.</note> when hee was taken up into the third heaven; and to S. <hi>John,</hi> in Patmos in the Spirit.</p>
            <p>Object. But ſome may object, and ſay, <hi>If wee ſee God thorow a glaſſe, then wee ſee him cleerly:</hi> Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum enim non rei imaginem, ſed rem ipſam ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis exhibet; <hi>A glaſſe doth not ſet forth to us the image of the thing, but the thing it ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> True, a glaſſe doth demonſtrate the thing it ſelfe to the eye; yet ſo, that ſtill it is <hi>per radium non directum, ſed reflexum,</hi> by a ray or beam not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, but reflexed; and therefore not properly, clearly, and diſtinctly; but at a diſtance, obſcure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and confuſedly: and ſuch is our knowledge of God and divine myſteries in this mortall life, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as through a glaſſe darkly, <hi>per ſpeculare,</hi> as through ſpectacles, which, you know, make things legible and viſible which before were not, and that, <hi>per medium obſcurum, &amp; ſimilitudinem umbro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam;</hi> or, as the Apoſtle, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in a riddle;</hi> or, as in my Text, <hi>per cancellos, per tranſennam,</hi> as tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row grates or latteſſes, which is a Metaphoricall ſpeech borrowed from merchants, or tradeſ-men, <hi>qui per cancellos vimineos expandunt mercaturas,</hi> who thorow grates or latteſſes expoſe their wares for ſale, and to be viewed by ſuch as paſſe along, <hi>non propè, ſed procul; non diſtinctè, ſed confuſo modo:</hi> not nigh at hand, but at a diſtance; not diſtinctly, but confuſedly. And thus Almighty God manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelfe to us in this life, not really and fully apparent, but as from behind a wall, as thorow grates or latteſſes.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:159596:47"/>
            <p>And yet not altogether ſo obſcurely, as that no knowledge can be had of him, but that a true Chriſtian, by the eye of unblemiſhed faith, may be aſſured that there he ſtands; for, ſaith his Spouſe, <hi>Behold, hee ſtandeth behind our wall:</hi> which is the fourth Generall of the Text.</p>
            <q>Behold, hee ſtandeth behinde our wall, hee looketh forth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>By the way (I pray) obſerve, that this word [<hi>behold</hi>] is not to be underſtood in this place as a note of attention, but of demonſtration, <hi>quaſi Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia digito monstravit, quem corde dilexit;</hi> as if his Spouſe pointed him out with her finger, whom ſhe loved in her heart: <hi>Behold, he ſtandeth,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But how is his Spouſe aſſured of his voice and preſence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reſol. <hi>Per viſibilia inviſibilem:</hi> by things vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and audible, ſhee is aſcertained that it is onely hee; for ſhee is aſſured, that it is his <hi>voice that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 5. 2.</note> 
               <hi>knocketh,</hi> and calleth to her to open unto him; ſhe is aſſured that ſhee ſeeth him in the variety and beauty of the creatures; ſhee is aſſured that ſhee heareth him in the book of the Scriptures; ſhee is aſſured that ſhee feeleth him in the checks of her conſcience; ſhee is aſſured that ſhee ſmelleth him<note place="margin">Cant. 5. 13.</note> in the fragrancy of his graces; and ſhee is aſſured that ſhee taſteth him in the ſweetneſſe of his word, which the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> calleth <hi>ſincere milk:</hi> and<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 2, 3. Heb. 6. 4.</note> the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, the good word of God.</hi> Theſe are the windows thorow which God ſhineth inwardly upon her ſoul: <hi>Haec quaſi ſpeculum Creatorem ſuum repraeſentant;</hi> God through theſe manifeſteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſo farre unto her, as ſhee is able to apprehend
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:159596:47"/> him in them and by them. <hi>Ex effectibus Dei de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrari</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aquin.</note> 
               <hi>poteſt Deum eſſe, licèt per eos effectus non poſsimus eum perfectè cognoſcere ſecundùm ſuam Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam;</hi> By the works of God it is evident that there is a God, although even by thoſe works wee cannot perfectly diſcern his Eſſence. Yet <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, what may be known of God by the light of nature, is manifeſted in the creature; as that there is a God, that there is but one God, that hee is Eternall, Omnipotent, the ſole Creator of heaven and earth, and all therein; that hee is moſt holy, moſt wiſe, and moſt juſt, the rewarder of the godly, and the puniſher of the wicked: But yet this light of nature is not of it ſelfe ſufficient, unleſſe it be holpen by a ſupernaturall light: For, <hi>Non potuerint Gentiles per ſolum naturae lumen unum agnoſcere ſolum eſſe Deum:</hi> the Heathen by the dim light of nature were not able to know that this God is but One.</p>
            <p>To thoſe therefore, whom the holy Spirit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to diſcern God, the ſame Spirit conferreth the ſpirit of wiſdome and ſanctified knowledge, by means whereof they doe ſee God: Hence that ſpeech of Chriſt, <hi>Hee that ſeeth mee, ſeeth my Father</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 14. 9.</note> 
               <hi>alſo;</hi> ſcil. <hi>opere Spiritûs ſancti,</hi> namely, by the work of the holy Ghoſt. On the contrary, they, the eyes of whoſe ſoules the holy Ghoſt hath not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned with the ſaving beams of divine truth, can never ſee or know the Father in the Son.</p>
            <p>As then none is ſaid to touch Chriſt, when the<note place="margin">Mar. 5. 30, 31.</note> multitude thronged him, ſave onely ſhee who had the bloudy iſſue; ſo none is properly ſaid to ſee Chriſt, ſave onely ſuch, in whom the holy Ghoſt
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:159596:48"/> hath wrought faith to beleeve him and his word, for it is impoſſible without faith (which is the eye of the ſoule) either to ſee him, or know him; and according to each mans faith, ſo ſhall it be unto him.</p>
            <p>For we muſt know, that there is a twofold ſight,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Of the body.</item>
               <item>2. Of the minde.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The eye of the body cannot ſee God, for he is inviſible, his Eſſence is ſpirituall; and if a man cannot ſee his own ſpirit, much leſſe can hee ſee God, <hi>who is the Father of ſpirits.</hi> Now if it be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected,<note place="margin">Heb. 12. 9. Exod. 33. 11. Gen. 17. 1.</note> that <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw God. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that they ſaw not his ſubſtance, hee only ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in ſimilitudes, by which hee teſtified his preſence. But <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, <hi>In my fleſh I ſhall ſee God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job. 9. 26.</note> 
               <hi>and mine owne eyes ſhall behold him. Anſw.</hi> By God in that place is meant the ſecond perſon of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, who being God, was incarnate, and ſo God may be ſeen in Chriſt. But <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that <hi>we ſhall ſee God face to face. Anſw.</hi> God hath not members<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 12.</note> as we have; but this is ſpoken <hi>per</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our humane capacitie; and the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, that we ſhall have ſuch a full knowledge of God, as wee have of him whom wee do ſee face to face. But ſhall our eyes ſerve us for no uſe in heaven? <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yes: with them wee ſhall behold the glorious Saints, and Chriſt our Judge and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, glorified in his humane nature, whom to<note place="margin">Acts 3. 13.</note> behold yeelds unconceivable comfort.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond is the ſight of the minde, which in this life is imperfect, and only ſeeth God in his works and word, &amp;c. by which wee may gather
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:159596:48"/> the great love of God towards us, in exhibiting himſelfe ſo farre: but that perfect ſight which the minde ſhall then have of God, is reſerved till here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, when ſeeing him, wee ſhall be transformed into his image.</p>
            <p>This ſight of the minde which properly is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the ſoule, is twofold:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Simple; as when a man ſees a thing abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, and as it is in it ſelfe: thus God cannot be ſeen, by reaſon of his Immenſity, filling all places.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Comprehenſive; namely, when a man ſeeth God ſo farre forth as hee is capable of the knowledge of him: and in this ſenſe wee ſhall ſee God perfectly in the world to come, and be filled with the fruition of his preſence, as a veſſell may be filled with the water of the ſea, though it hold not all the water of the ſea.</p>
            <p>In this comprehenſive manner, as the Spouſe of Chriſt is ſure that ſhee ſeeth him, ſo is ſhee ſure alſo that ſhee heareth him; for, ſaith ſhee, in the verſe preceding the Text, <hi>Behold, the voice of my Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved:</hi> ſhee was a partaker of the firſt reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo heard his voice, which enlivened her<note place="margin">John 4. 25.</note> ſoule; and ſhee was ſure that it was his voice in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and not a ſtrangers, their often mutuall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference had given her an exact knowledge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: As then the true Spouſe of Chriſt can onely rightly diſcern Chriſts voice; ſo, whoſoever hath not plighted his faith to him, knowes it not from the voice of a ſtranger, and ſo may ſoon be delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as may appeare by <hi>Ahab,</hi> giving credit to the <hi>lying ſpirit</hi> in the mouthes of his falſe prophets.<note place="margin">1 King. 22. 22.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:159596:49"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:159596:49"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:159596:50"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:159596:50"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:159596:51"/>
            <p>Object. But ſome may object that ſaying of Chriſt, <hi>No man knoweth the Son, but the Father: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 11. 27.</note> 
               <hi>knoweth any man the Father, ſave the Son, and hee to whomſoever the Son will reveal him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> The words are to be underſtood compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively; that is, as the knowledge of the Son is originally in God the Father, and it is by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers revealing of the Son, that any come to know the Son, that is, to beleeve in his Name: ſo the knowledge of the Father is originally in the Son, and it muſt be by the Sonnes revealing of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that any can come to know him. Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently therefore ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> None know the<note place="margin">Chryſost.</note> Father with that knowledge with which the Son knoweth him, that is, fully to obey him and in all things perfectly to conforme to his will, which is knowledge unto ſalvation. Of this perfection of knowledge, which is ſolely in Chriſt, the beſt of Gods children come ſhort in this life: 'Tis true, they know him, and ſee him, but here it is weakly and imperfectly, as from behinde a wall. Or thus: As by ſeeing a piece of coine, a man may know whoſe coine it is by the image and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription engraven thereon; ſo the Spouſe of Chriſt knoweth whoſe image is engraven in the heavens, and who that is that ſhewes himſelfe in the windowes of the Scriptures, and in the grates of Conſcience. Or thus: As by ſeeing a picture, a man may know whom it repreſents, eſpecially if there hath been any former acquaintance; ſo the Church (which is Chriſts Spouſe) ſeeing the face of God in the light of the Scriptures, and the beauty of the Creatures, exactly knowes whoſe it
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:159596:51"/> is. So that, unleſſe our faith be turned into infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and the light of our underſtanding into the darkneſſe of ignorance, wee cannot but ſee him who ſanctifies his Church, who ſoftens our hearts, who quickens us by his Spirit, and who enlighten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth our ſoules by driving away the foggy miſts of our naturall blindneſſe.</p>
            <p>And here, give me leave to make a little digreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and, I hope, not altogether impertinent. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, hee ſtandeth behinde our wall:</hi> Some by <hi>wall</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cornel. à Lap.</note> would underſtand mans incredulity, as having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to that of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, Your iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 59. 2.</note> 
               <hi>have ſeparated twixt you and your God, and your ſins have hid his face from you.</hi> Others underſtand that <hi>thick cloud</hi> which was between God and the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites<note place="margin">Exod. 19. 16.</note> at the giving of the Law, <hi>ex qua procedebant coruſcationes, adeo ut Iſraelitici tremuêre,</hi> out of which went fearfull lightnings, which made the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites to tremble. Others, the ceremoniall Law, which was afterwards abrogated, when <hi>the partiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 2. 14.</note> 
               <hi>wall</hi> was <hi>broken down.</hi> Others, the Prophets, who myſtically ſet forth Chriſt to come. Others, the humanity of Chriſt; ſo ſaith S. <hi>John,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Word was made fleſh;</hi> O bleſſed ſalve to<note place="margin">John 1. 14.</note> clear our ſight! Take wee all, or either of theſe,<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Joh. tract. 2.</note> and they ſet forth the love of him who is, or at leaſt ſhould be, the joy of our hearts, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of our eyes. Nor may it be thought vain-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious preſumption if I interpoſe mine opinion: By <hi>wall</hi> therefore I underſtand protection and ſafety wrought by a prudent and faithfull Magiſtracie, ſuch Magiſtrates being as walls and bulwarks to preſerve a people from ruine and deſolation, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:159596:52"/> by the ſubtill plots of cunning <hi>Ahithophels,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 17. Eſth. 3. Amos 7. 10.</note> bloud-thirſty <hi>Hamans,</hi> and idolatrous <hi>Amaziah's.</hi> And if wee take it in this ſenſe, wee cannot but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that God hath ſtood for our good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde our wall, in that hee hath made our vigilant Patriots to be to us as <hi>David</hi> and his ſervants were to <hi>Nabal</hi> and his ſervants, <hi>a wall both by night and</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25. 16.</note> 
               <hi>by day:</hi> And becauſe they have laboured to <hi>take</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 15. 19.</note> 
               <hi>forth the precious from the vile,</hi> therefore hath the Lord made them unto his Church as <hi>a fenced bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 20.</note> 
               <hi>wall.</hi> What although men fight againſt them, yet they ſhall not prevail: for God, by the mouth of his Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> hath promiſed, that hee will be <hi>with</hi> them, <hi>to ſave</hi> them, <hi>and deliver</hi> them:<note place="margin">Jer. 15. 19, 20, 21.</note> yea, hee <hi>will deliver</hi> them <hi>out of the hand of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and redeem</hi> them <hi>out of the hand of the terrible.</hi> So that wee may well ſing that ſong of <hi>Iſaiah, Wee</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 26. 1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>have a ſtrong citie, ſalvation will the Lord appoint for walls and bulwarks. Open yee the gates, that the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous nation which keepeth the truth may enter in.</hi> Yea, wee may juſtly ſay, that the Lord hath been both to them and us <hi>a wall of fire round about,</hi> and will be<note place="margin">Zech. 2. 5.</note> 
               <hi>the glory in the midſt of</hi> his people.</p>
            <p>And now I come to the fifth or laſt Generall of my Text; namely, that the Spouſe of Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſured that thus ſhe doth ſee him, may rejoice with comfort, and be raviſhed with deſire of a greater union and communion with him.</p>
            <p>This doth conſummate whatſoever tends to the perfection of happineſſe: In it wee are to obſerve two things;</p>
            <p n="1">1. That to ſee God yeelds comfort to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this life.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:159596:52"/>2. That to be made one with God crowns all with eternall felicitie.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That to ſee God yeelds comfort to the godly, not to the divels and reprobate; for their ſight ſhall be their ſorrow: they ſhall indeed ſee him, not as their Saviour, but as their Judge, to ſentence them to eternall puniſhment: <hi>Every eye</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 1. 7.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall ſee him, they alſo which pierced him;</hi> but yet, as it followeth, they <hi>ſhall waile becauſe of him:</hi> their ſight ſhall rather afright them, then any way mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the leaſt crum of comfort to them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That therefore wee may ſee God with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, Mark we what Chriſt teacheth; wee muſt be<note place="margin">Matth. 5. 8.</note> 
               <hi>pure in heart:</hi> Now hee is ſaid thus to be pure, whoſe heart mindeth not unchaſte things; ſo <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſ. Hom. 15.</note> Or he is ſaid to be pure, whoſe heart is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes free from malice, and continually addicted to temperance; ſo the ſame Father. <hi>Calvin</hi> ſtileth<note place="margin">Calvin.</note> that heart pure, which is not crafty or deceitfull. <hi>Perkins</hi> calleth that heart pure, which is firſt truely<note place="margin">Perkins.</note> humble in ſenſe of ſins paſt, reſolving ever after to live more holily, and not to ſin againſt God any longer wilfully: Secondly, which teſtifieth this humilitie, by labouring exact obedience to the will of God; for a pure heart, and a wicked con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation cannot ſtand together. A reſolution therefore not to ſin, is an evident mark of a ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ſoule, and of a pure heart, which ſhall ſee God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That wee may ſee God with comfort, wee muſt endeavour to draw neer God now in this time of grace; for the neerer wee are thus to him, the cleerer wee ſhall diſcern him: which that wee
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:159596:53"/> may doe, wee muſt ſet God alwayes before our<note place="margin">Pſal. 16. 8.</note> eyes; and remember, that whatſoever wee think, ſpeak, or doe, or whereſoever wee are, we alwaies are in his ſight; <hi>Walk</hi> we therefore <hi>before</hi> God, <hi>and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 17. 1.</note> 
               <hi>be</hi> wee <hi>perfect</hi> was Gods precept to <hi>Abraham.</hi> O that all called to eminent places would remember this!</p>
            <p n="3">3. That we may ſee God with comfort, uſe we the means ordained by God; that is, frequent wee his houſe; there God manifeſteth his preſence moſt gloriouſly. It was <hi>Davids</hi> prayer to God, that hee might not be debarred the beholding of <hi>the beauty of the Lord</hi> in his houſe, and <hi>enquiring in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 27. 4.</note> 
               <hi>his temple.</hi> The like reſpect have wee to his word and ſacraments; for in thoſe hee manifeſteth his beauty as well as in his Sanctuarie: receive wee them as pledges of his love and goodneſſe towards us, and they ſhall be as a ladder, by which we may aſcend to perfect happineſſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Remember wee what an horrour it is not to ſee God: now God is ſaid to hide himſelfe from the wicked. As then the ſight of <hi>Davids</hi> face was <hi>the light of Iſrael;</hi> ſo is the ſight of Gods face the<note place="margin">2 Sam. 21. 17.</note> light of his choſen, <hi>In his preſence is life, and in his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 90. 17. Pſal. 30. 5. Pſal. 16. 11.</note> 
               <hi>light wee ſhall ſee light:</hi> yea, <hi>In his preſence is fulneſſe of joy, and at his right hand are pleaſures for evermore.</hi> The Queen of Sheba reckoned <hi>Solomons</hi> ſervants happy, becauſe they did ſtand before him, and hear<note place="margin">1 King. 10. 8.</note> his wiſdome: ſo and much more happy are the children of God, who ſtand before him continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and ſee his glory. If <hi>Moſes</hi> was happy in that hee ſaw Gods back-parts; or the diſciples of Chriſt, who ſaw his glory in his transfiguration:
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:159596:53"/> O, what joy ſhall it be to the Spouſe of Chriſt to ſee her beloved clothed with robes of Majeſtie! O! ſay wee then, as ſometimes <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid to God in behalfe of himſelf and the whole congregation, <hi>If thy preſence goe not with us, carry us not hence: For</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exo. 33. 15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>wherein ſhall it be known that</hi> wee <hi>thy people have found grace in thy ſight? Is it not in that thou goeſt with us</hi> in this vale of miſery, and wilderneſſe of woe? And pray wee, with <hi>David,</hi> that the Lord would cauſe his face to ſhine upon us, and <hi>lift up</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 4. 7.</note> 
               <hi>the light of</hi> his <hi>countenance;</hi> for his face is favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, it rejoyceth the heart, it reviveth the ſoul, and<note place="margin">Prov. 19. 12.</note> is <hi>as the dew upon the tender graſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude this point; This cannot but mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter great comfort to the godly, in that, although after many reproaches in this life, God only look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon them as thorow a glaſſe, yet hereafter they ſhall be ſure to behold him face to face: Wherefore, <hi>Hear yee the word of the Lord, you that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 66. 5.</note> 
               <hi>tremble at his word: your brethren that hated you, and caſt you out for my Names ſake, ſaid, Let the Lord be glorified: but hee ſhall appear to your joy, and they ſhall be aſhamed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our ſecond point was, That to be made one with God by an holy union, crowns all with eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall felicity.</p>
            <p>The chiefeſt and moſt ardent deſire of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full here, is to gain aſſurance of eternall happineſſe hereafter: this Chriſt hath promiſed, and this hee will make good, when the day of his eſpouſals ſhall come, which alſo is at the day of judgement. 'Tis true, this is the time of their wooing, in which the Spouſe knowes her Beloved but in part; but then
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:159596:54"/> ſhee ſhall know him as hee is, for ſhe ſhall be made one with him, <hi>all glorious within.</hi> In this life hee<note place="margin">Pſal. 4 5. 13.</note> gives her evident teſtimonies of his more ardent love, as the gift of regeneration, of obedience to his will and word, of faith to beleeve his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, of confidence to relie on him for protection in times of danger, and of prayer to importune him fervently: Adde to theſe the knowledge of reconciliation, the inward comforts of his Spirit in times of temptation, and ſtrength to perſevere in times of fiery triall. Theſe graces hee beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, as pledges of his love, onely on his Spouſe, and ſhee as highly priſeth them.</p>
            <p>Nor doth Chriſt beſtow all his favours onely on his choſen; but, as hee that is a ſuiter to a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man giveth ſome gifts to houſhold ſervants, yet keepeth his prime jewels of value onely for her on whom his love is fixed: ſo Chriſt beſtoweth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon favours even on the wicked, thereby making known his riches; yet his choice and ſelected gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the enjoyment of his love, hee ſolely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth for his beloved Spouſe, who affectionately locks them up in the cloſet of her heart: ſo that ſhee ſeemeth to ſpeak in the words of <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> (when <hi>David</hi> returned ſafe from battell) concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Ziba; Let him take all, foraſmuch as my lord the king is returned again in peace unto his own houſe:</hi> So ſhee, as undervaluing all earthly things in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of the enjoyment of Chriſt his preſence and graces, Let whoſo will take all theſe, only let me enjoy my Beloved, and let my ſoule be filled with the graces of his Spirit.</p>
            <p>And no marvell that the ſoules of Chriſtians are
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:159596:54"/> thus raviſhed with the deſire of an union with Chriſt, which (<hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) is beſt of all, in regard of that felicity wherewith both ſoule and body ſhall then be dignified in the new Jeruſalem, that heavenly Canaan:</p>
            <p>Firſt, In regard of the felicitie of the body, which conſiſteth in its change (after the generall reſurrection) from being a corruptible body, to be a glorious body; for that which is now cumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and infeſted with many miſeries, ſubject to mutation, vexed with diſeaſes, defiled with cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and repleniſhed with innumerable calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſhall then be made moſt glorious, perfect, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver durable without mutation, it ſhall be freed from a decaying eſtate, and placed in an ever-flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing condition; yea, the whole body ſhall be glorified, and being glorified, ſhall be filled with all fulneſſe of contentment; eyes, ears, mouth, noſe, hands, and heart with unutterable ſweetneſſe: <hi>They</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 36. 8.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall be abundantly ſatisfied with the fatneſſe of thy houſe, and thou ſhalt make them drink of the river of thy pleaſures:</hi> beſides, death ſhall have no domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over it, for the juſt ſhall live for ever. Chriſt ſetting forth the felicity of the righteous, ſaith, that <hi>the righteous ſhall ſhine forth as the Sun in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 13. 43.</note> 
               <hi>of their Father;</hi> which proves the glory of their bodies. <hi>Et quanta tunc erit gloria animarum, quando Solis habebit claritatem lux corporum?</hi> How gloriouſly ſhall their ſouls be inveſted, when their bodies ſhall ſhine like the Sun in the firmament? which is the ſecond part of a Chriſtians felicitie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In regard of the felicitie of the ſoule; and this conſiſteth chiefly <hi>in viſione Dei beatifica,</hi>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:159596:55"/> in the beatificall viſion of God; <hi>Haec ſola ſummum</hi>
               <note place="margin">August. lib. de Trin. cap. 13.</note> 
               <hi>eſt bonum,</hi> this is the chiefeſt good: This alſo St. <hi>Paul</hi> averreth, when he ſaith, that <hi>we ſhall ſee God face to face:</hi> The like alſo doth S. <hi>John,</hi> when hee ſaith, that <hi>we ſhall ſee him (qualis eſt) as he is:</hi> and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe <hi>Ibi tota erit virtus, videre quod ames;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de Civ. Dei.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; tota felicitas, amare quod videas: ibi beata vita in ſuo fonte bibitur, ubi veritatis viſio clariſsimè aperitur.</hi> All the contentations in the world are but as ſmall ſparkles ſent forth from God, in whom they are moſt perfect and excellent: All the perfections of his creatures are more perfect in him then they are in themſelves: whoſo then enjoyeth the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, hath full felicity preſented to him at once, ſo that hee cannot wiſh for any good, but there he findeth it in its full perfection; yea, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever deſerveth love or admiration: All the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of the ſoule, and all the ſenſes of the body ſhall be ſatisfied with the fruition of the preſence and glory of God. In a word, God ſhall be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall happineſſe to all his elect; for, by enjoying his preſence, they ſhall alſo enjoy whatſoever is delightfull: by enjoying his preſence, they ſhall know the ſecret judgements of God, which are a great depth: by enjoying Gods preſence, they ſhall love God above all, and their fellow-ſaints equally as themſelves, and for the ſame cauſes for which they are themſelves beloved of God: by enjoying Gods preſence, they ſhall rejoyce at their owne happineſſe, for they ſhall enter into their Maſters joy. It is not ſaid, that the joy of their Maſter ſhall enter into them, becauſe no created heart can receive the fulneſſe of this joy; but they
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:159596:55"/> ſhall enter into the joy of their Maſter. Laſtly, by enjoying Gods preſence, they ſhall, with the holy Angels (whom <hi>Auguſtine</hi> calls <hi>Hymnidici chori</hi>)<note place="margin">Aug. in Johan.</note> praiſe God without ceaſing, with a perfect heart, freely; ſo the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Bleſſed are they that dwell</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 84. 4.</note> 
               <hi>in thy houſe, they will be ſtill praiſing thee.</hi> To ſumme up all together; In this beholding of Gods face, the ſaints ſhall know the power of God the Father, the wiſdome of God the Son, and the goodneſſe of God the holy Ghoſt, which is the joy of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, which is the reward of eternall life, which is the glory of the bleſſed ſpirits, the new Jeruſalem, the perfection of bliſſe, and that <hi>peace which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all underſtanding;</hi> by vertue whereof they ſhall praiſe God, and praiſing him love him, and loving him poſſeſſe him, who is the inheritance of his people; witneſſe his promiſe to <hi>Abraham, I will</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 15. 1.</note> 
               <hi>be thine exceeding great reward.</hi> O! ſay we all then, O Lord, thou art in thy ſelfe exceeding great, and therefore thou muſt needs be an exceeding great reward: It is life everlaſting to ſee thee, it <hi>is life</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 17. 3.</note> 
               <hi>everlaſting to know thee, and whom thou hast ſent, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi> If then the wiſe men rejoyced to ſee Chriſt in the manger, what joy will it be to ſee him in his glory? If old <hi>Abraham rejoyced to ſee</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 8. 56. <hi>Aug. Tract. 43. in Johan.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>day</hi> of Chriſt yet afarre off (for hee rejoyced through hope that he ſhould ſee it by underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it) <hi>and hee ſaw it,</hi> then which, what greater joy could be expreſſed? for, if they rejoyce who have their bodily eyes opened, what joy doth the unutterable light of the ſoule bring? If a bride re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joiceth, not onely when ſhe hears the voice of her bridegroom, but more affectionately when ſhee
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:159596:56"/> enjoyeth his preſence, becauſe <hi>they twaine ſhall be one fleſh;</hi> Or, if a loving wife rejoiceth when her husband returneth ſafe after a long and tedious journey: So and much more doth the ſoule of a Chriſtian rejoice, when ſhee is united to Chriſt her head.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee what inexpreſſible conſolation this union of Chriſt yeeldeth to all the children of the firſt reſurrection: Firſt, in that they ſhall be ſo changed, as that they ſhall be made capable of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall glory. Secondly, in that death ſhall no more be terrible, becauſe their bodies ſhall be no more ſinfull.</p>
            <p>And herein the godly differ from the wicked in three reſpects:</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the Cauſes: for the wicked ſhall indeed riſe, but it is by reaſon of Gods ſummons, when the trumpet ſhall blow, and all muſt of neceſſity appeare; whereas the godly riſe to be united to their head Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the Manner: for the wicked riſe with horrour and griefe; whereas the godly riſe with joy and comfort.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the End: for the wicked riſe to eternall confuſion; whereas the godly riſe to everlaſting glorification: They that live in Chriſt ſhall ſleep in Chriſt, and <hi>ſuch as ſleep in Chriſt, God will bring</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4. 14, 17.</note> 
               <hi>with him, and</hi> they <hi>ſhall be ever with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, This union of the godly with Chriſt ſhall be glorious in regard of their cohabitation: for the wicked, after ſentence pronounced by Chriſt (who then ſhall ſit as Judge,) ſhall be hurled into hell, a place loathſome and grievous, becauſe
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:159596:56"/> of that ſtinke which never ſhall be abated, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of that pain that never ſhall be ended: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the godly ſhall be enthronized in a <hi>kingdom pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them from the beginning of the world,</hi> which is a kingdome of bliſſe, in which they ſhall live e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally.</p>
            <p>So then, as the pains of the one place are univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall, ſo are the pleaſures of the other univerſall alſo: Pain and pleaſure in this life are temporall, in the other they are eternall; and as the torture of the one (in regard of the loſſe of Chriſts preſence) is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſible, ſo the comfort of the other (in the fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of his preſence) is unconceivable. With old <hi>Simeon</hi> then, who rejoiced to embrace Chriſt in his arms at the time of his preſentation, let all true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted profeſſors rejoice, in that Chriſt will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them to his Father when the time ſhall come for their glorification: In the mean time, while we ſee him <hi>ſtanding behinde our wall,</hi> let us ſing with that old <hi>Simeon, Lord, now letteſt thou thy ſervant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part in peace, for mine eyes have ſeen</hi> the Prince of peace, <hi>thy ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag. 7. lin. 22. for</hi> moſt, <hi>reade</hi> more. <hi>p. 10. l. 27. for</hi> as, <hi>r.</hi> us, <hi>p. 26. l. 2. for</hi> unto <hi>r.</hi> to. <hi>p. 34. l. 21. for</hi> for, <hi>r.</hi> forth.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
